<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Effigies amoris in English, or, The picture of love unveil'd</title>
            <title>Amoris effigies. English. 1682</title>
            <author>Waring, Robert, 1614-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67614</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38066</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17164356</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17164356</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106094</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67614)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106094)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1161:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Effigies amoris in English, or, The picture of love unveil'd</title>
                  <title>Amoris effigies. English. 1682</title>
                  <author>Waring, Robert, 1614-1658.</author>
                  <author>Phil-icon-erus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 126, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. White for James Good ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Other eds. show authors name on t.p.</note>
                  <note>Contains marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Epistle deicatory signed: Phil-icon-erus.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [3] at end.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [5] at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Love.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106094:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:106094:1"/>
               <hi>Effigies Amoris</hi> IN ENGLISH: OR THE PICTURE OF Love Unveil'd.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Euſtathius de Iſmeniae &amp; Iſmenes Amoribus. <bibl>
                  <hi>Lib. 3. p. 97.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. White,</hi> for <hi>James Good,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Oxford.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106094:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106094:2"/>
            <head>THE PICTURE OF Love Unveil'd.</head>
            <head type="sub">Humbly dedicated to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, <hi>M. A.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE reaſon why I thought fit to dedicate this Novel to a <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> was becauſe the ſubject is ſoft and feminine; but the powerful biaſs which deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd
<pb facs="tcp:106094:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:106094:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:106094:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:106094:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:106094:5"/>
my Choice to <hi>you</hi> for its Patroneſs were thoſe many and great Obligations which you have upon me; whereby like Heaven you claim a right to all my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours. I ſay a right, for I am far from the vanity of thinking this or any other preſent I can make you ſuch a <hi>free-will-</hi>offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as may in the leaſt pretend to be <hi>meritorious.</hi> No Madam, you have ſo much got the <hi>Start</hi> of me in Obligations, and have ſuch an anticipating <hi>Mortgage</hi> on the reſidue of my actions, that I can do you no piece of ſervice, which you had not a Title to before: Like Votaries in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who cannot burn Incenſe to the Gods, but with their own perfumes. But though we are not ſo <hi>Impiouſly</hi> vain, as to think we oblige Heaven when we erect Altars, and Conſecrate Temples; yet Religion allows us to expect, and the Divine good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb facs="tcp:106094:5"/>
vouchſaſes us favourable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance But to queſtion my ſucceſs in that, were to meaſure your goodneſs by the narrowneſs of my own merit. Eſpecially ſince the Oblation is attended with ſo much devotion, and in the moſt <hi>Literal</hi> ſenſe is all over <hi>Love.</hi> And this gives me occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſay a word or two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the work it ſelf. That which I here preſent you with, is the Picture of Love, a very excellent <hi>piece,</hi> drawn to the life in every <hi>Feature.</hi> This admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Picture (ſo natural is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty to great and true worth) has a long time conceal'd it ſelf under a foreign veil, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of which, I have added one degree of goodneſs more to its many excellencies, <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi> Indeed I thought it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, ſince <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> are things equally implan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the hearts of all mankind,
<pb facs="tcp:106094:6"/>
that the myſteries of one ſhould be contain'd in an unknown Tongue, more than thoſe of the other. And now Madam I have one more Dedication to you, and that is of my ſelf, who am with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all imaginable ſincerity, your moſt devoted Servant,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Phil-icon-erus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:106094:6"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Author of this Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation thinks fit to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Reader, that although he admires</hi> Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figies Amoris <hi>as an Author which for ſweetneſs of fancy, neatneſs of Stile, and luſciouſneſs of</hi> hidden <hi>ſenſe may compare to ſay no more, with any extant; yet he has not been ſo</hi> Judaically <hi>ſuperſtitious, as to adhere to every minute Phraſe, or particle of ſenſe; contenting himſelf that he has not let any one thought of</hi> moment <hi>eſcape him. Juſtice to the Author requires the one, and the priviledge of a Tranſlator ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies the other. For certainly that
<pb facs="tcp:106094:7"/>
verbal and ſervile way of Tranſlating, is the worſt ridiculing of a well Penn'd diſcourſe that can be, and ſerves for no end, but only to help out a deſpairing School-boy, at a dead lift. Yet leſt any ſhould ſuſpect this as a pre-contrived Apology for a too licentious Innovation, he would have them obſerve, that where the Authors Idiom will fall in natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with our own (which is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, for he does not take</hi> [I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diom] <hi>in that rigorous ſenſe, as Logicians do their</hi> proprium quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to modo, <hi>but only for a true cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary meaſure of ſpeaking, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in languages may ſometimes agree, and ſometimes not) he prefers it, which is enough to acquit him from that charge. In the next place he deſires that none would pretend to Criticize on the</hi> Tranſlation <hi>but thoſe who throughly underſtand the</hi> Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal; <hi>and then he thinks he ſhall have but</hi> few <hi>and thoſe</hi> Judicious <hi>Criticks. For certainly the ſenſe
<pb facs="tcp:106094:7"/>
of this Author lies ſo far in, that 'tis not to be ſeen through by a</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blind <hi>apprehenſion, no nor by a</hi> Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory <hi>glance of the moſt</hi> quickſight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>mind. His thoughts are ſo nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, ſublime and depending, his images of things ſo fine-wrought and pathetical, his method ſo ſecret and lurking, yet withal ſo accurate, that they require as much adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of mind as a Mathematical demonſtration. Nay there are ſome ſuch myſtical and exalted Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in him, as can ſcarce be reach'd but by a Reader almoſt</hi> Dieted <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a</hi> Platoniſt, <hi>and, as</hi> Des-Cartes <hi>ſaies of his Metaphyſical meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, cannot be underſtood as they ſhould be; but by a mind ſequeſtr'd from all</hi> Commerce <hi>with the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. The Judicious reader will think this no Hyperbole, when he ſhall find that after he has thought himſelf poſſeſs'd of the very mind and</hi> ſoul. <hi>of the Author upon a review or more leiſurely inſpection, he will
<pb facs="tcp:106094:8"/>
diſcern new thoughts like little Stars glimmering out of the rich</hi> Galaxy, <hi>and ſpring a</hi> mine <hi>of</hi> undiſcovered <hi>ſenſe. And then the found Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, beſides the ſweetneſs of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, will abundantly recompence the pains of the moſt diligont en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry. Here you have Love tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced through all its various notions and acceptations, and repreſented in the moſt perfect and refined Idea of each: the meaſures and Offices of Friendſhip ſtated, true generous Friendſhips diſtinguiſh'd from thoſe mercenary and ſenſual aſſociations, which uſurp that ſacred, name, ſuch as</hi> Plutarch <hi>calls</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Idols and</hi> Apes <hi>of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, an account of almoſt all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thology, wherein the paſſions are ſo ſweetly repreſented, as to make a</hi> Stoick <hi>in Love with them; and all this perform'd with the</hi> Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſs <hi>of a Moraliſt, tho' yet with the</hi> Elegance <hi>of a Rhetorician. To mention but one Commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:106094:8"/>
more which muſt not be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Nil dictu foedum viſuve haec li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina tangit.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Here is nothing immodeſt or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcene, no thoughts which would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit a ſtate of</hi> innocence, <hi>or profane the</hi> Cell <hi>of an Hermite. In the moſt ſenſitive Images of Love and Paſſion, the modeſt</hi> Apelles <hi>has drawn</hi> Venus <hi>but to the</hi> Waſt. <hi>But 'tis impoſſible to repreſent this Author as well as he has done Love; neither indeed does he need any commendatory</hi> Paſs-port, <hi>he carries worth enough with him to approve him to all thoſe that underſtand him.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106094:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106094:9"/>
            <head>Some body being very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive to know what Love was, the Author returns him this anſwer.</head>
            <p>I Am too Senſible of the <hi>Wanton</hi> Tyranny of <hi>Imperious</hi> Love, and with what ſevere trials it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly exerciſes the affections. But although to Love be as great a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as any of <hi>Hercules</hi>'s, ſince it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually impoſes new tasks and Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, allots us moſt <hi>Rigorous</hi> ſervices, and perverſly contrives to pleaſe with Cruelty: Yet nevertheleſs we are well content (we who have ſworn Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to Love) that it freely exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe this its unlimited dominion, that ſo the Auſterity of the impoſitions
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106094:10"/>
may magnifie both its own Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and our compliance. Let it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand us what is in our Power, and what is not in our Power (except this one thing, not to love) neither let it exact any thing below a miracle, ſince with the Command it gives abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, elevates the mind above it ſelf, and makes the man commence a Deity. So that he deſerves not the name <note place="margin">Lovers can do all things, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their ſtrength.</note> of a Lover, who does not act beyond the Sphere of All, and riſe up to his wiſhes by Heroical undertakings. No, he is but a Novice in Love who does not act ſomewhat above himſelf in obedience to his Paſſion.</p>
            <p>But you <hi>(my friend)</hi> with equity re-demand a draught of thoſe affections which you <note place="margin">Every one is the moſt pleaſing ſpectacle to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Whatever by ſhewing us to our ſelves doubles our embraces is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dear to us: But if it render us maim'd it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes dearer by defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity it ſelf.</note> your ſelf firſt taught me, though diveſted of your own grace and Elegancy. Is it becauſe it will be ſo delightſome to you to Contemplate the reflected Image of your ſelf, which is as lively engraven on my Devoted breaſt, as on an Adamantine Table: and will ſo pleaſe you to take a nice and Critical ſurvey of me as far as I may
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106094:10"/>
appear the workmanſhip of your own Art? Or is it becauſe your image can receive no diſadvantage from any ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh of the matter, but like the Sun gilds even the ſpots themſelves with its Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, that you will not like a peeviſh La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be diſpleas'd at your Looking-glaſs, for preſenting you with deformities which are none of your own, and as it were <hi>Burleſquing</hi> your face? I know not how it comes to paſs, but we have a kind of Love for the very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit ſhadows which are the reproach of our own bodies, and are apt to pay a more awful Veneration to mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Statues. So parents are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more tenderly affected toward their miſ-ſhapen Children (as if Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had ſo order'd it as a Solace to <note place="margin">Or from this very ſhew of injury or antiquiry.</note> misfortune) and treat theſe Monſters of the Womb with greater reverence, as if they were the preſages of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing extraordinary, Whereas all others deride the tranſpoſed Maſs of a diſtorted body, the <hi>Anagram</hi> of a <note place="margin">Deformity is a Sacred thing.</note> man. Certainly there is ſomething Sacred in deformity. The Prophets thought it more Divine than any beauty, more fit to repreſent the Grandeur of a Deity, and render an
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106094:11"/>
Oracle Majeſtick. It does at once ſcare Mortals and lecture them, and chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges not ſo much our Love as our adoration. Every one is the moſt pleaſing object and Charming ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle to himſelf, and the eye ſeems to be priviledged with the pleaſure of the mind, while it reflects its ſight upon it ſelf, being at once the object and the beholder. Whatever that is which by ſhewing us to our ſelves doubles our embraces, muſt needs be highly pretious. But if it repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent us maim'd and defective, it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a new value from the very ſhew of injury or antiquity. I am not therefore a little indebted to nature for making my mind a <hi>blank Table,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">'Tis the Myſtery of Love, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd, unleſs it be its own interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> though for no other reaſon than this, that it might receive ſo much of your Image, whereby it might delight both it ſelf and you. But <hi>'tis a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy</hi> (they ſay) <hi>when Images once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſpeak.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed I find it far eaſier to love, than to expreſs that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights only to be perceived, not to be ſhewn; and becauſe lodged in the receſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the heart, diſdains to admit the Tongue to be its conſort. That,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106094:11"/>
which none of us have learnt from <note place="margin">The Idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oms of Lovers like thoſe of Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors, are delivered in inver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters.</note> precedents and inſtructions, but then only begin to know when we we have all experimented it. You would ſay <hi>Cupid</hi> were not only <hi>blind</hi> but <hi>Dumb,</hi> ſince he renders every member of the body vocal except the Tongue. Hence 'tis that Lovers with more Eloquence communicate ſighs than words, as ſo many internunciary particles of vital Air, and like Doves of <hi>Venus</hi> mourn ſorth animated letters. Hence <note place="margin">They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſe like Angels by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuition, the will not the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining it ſelf.</note> 'tis that they keep a <hi>ſilent</hi> intercourſe with their fingers, now eloquent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Pen, and weave Dialogues in little Poſies. They hear one anothers mutual wiſhes, and read one anothers viſible ſouls, by thoſe vocal meſſengers of the affections, <hi>affable</hi> Nods, and <hi>darting</hi> Smiles. Sometimes their <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant</hi> geſtures compoſed as it were of ſo many rhetorical figures, court in a various and Myſterious Dialect. Sometimes their ranging aſpects are earneſtly fix'd on one another as on ſtrangers, and while they ſeem to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own all acquaintance, grow familiar by ſtealth. Sometimes their contracted brows pretend a paſſion, yet they do but all the while <hi>induſtriouſly</hi> fawne,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106094:12"/>
and <hi>deſignedly</hi> wait for delicate plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. Sometimes their ſouls inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably gliding from their eyes, take a Curſory taſte of <hi>Bride-kiſſes</hi> at a diſtance, and bring home their ſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len ſweets with Triumph. 'Tis at once their greateſt boaſt and pleaſure to remain undiſcover'd. Thus that which has ſo often appear'd in The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atres, does ſtill decline ſpectators, and acts its plaies in its <hi>own</hi> diſguiſe. Methinks theſe Divine converſers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a priviledge above the Laws of humane Commerce, thus to hit one anothers meanings by moſt infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible tokens, to pry into the very inward parts, and to entertain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a <hi>Divination</hi> rather than a Conference. For they are mutually diſcern'd by the clearer viſion of thought, before they deliver them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in words, or know how to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit; and their wiſhes become vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible like Phantoms, but withall like ſome Pictures cannot be underſtood with leſs art than was uſed in the making. They uncaſe themſelves of their bodies like gods quitting their Shrines, and not only expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to view, but intermix, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106094:12"/>
a ſoul into each other with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry accent. Their wandring and ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatic ſouls freely paſs to and fro as 'twere within the ſame body, and converſe as ſoftly as if in a Soliloquy. This one paſſion cannot poſſibly be expreſs'd, but is as a myſtery to be adored, whoſe Rites like ſome of greateſt antiquity among the gods, are ſhrowded no leſs than Crimes, with a baſhful ſecrecy. All Love has its veil, and the Votaries of <hi>Venus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">All Love has its veil.</note> like <hi>Aeneas</hi> go ſurrounded with a Cloud, and in the moſt popular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe enjoy a concealment. Neither does <hi>Cupid</hi> content himſelf with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle veil, but loves to view wounded hearts in <hi>Maſquerade,</hi> and to ſecure himſelf inviſible. So that Love, to whoſe friendly influence the orderly Syſtem of the Univerſe owes its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure, has left it ſelf in confuſion, bury'd in the Old Chaos and primitive obſcurity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Venus</hi> has hitherto avoided the Sun <note place="margin">Love is an unexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie.</note> as a betrayer of her ſecreſie; and to prevent diſcovery, ſome god or other has ſhut up <hi>all</hi> kind of Love as well as that of <hi>Paſiphae,</hi> in a Labyrinth, where if it chance to be taken, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106094:13"/>
all over intangled with Nets and Toiles; or confuſedly warpped up like a Monſter. Indeed every Lover is a Riddle and a blind Problem to <note place="margin">It is alſo a riddle.</note> himſelf. He lives <hi>Amphibiouſly,</hi> and is made up of contradictory paſſions, wafted up and down by thoſe alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate tides of his breaſt, ſo that from him you may learn that contrary winds and <hi>Seditious</hi> Waters gave birth to <hi>Venus.</hi> Is it ſo that the ſame perſon is <note place="margin">Love-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems.</note> enſlaved and yet acts with all freedom, is maſter of his own will, yet at the ſame time ſubject to anothers, and like the manumiſs'd Slaves of Emperors purchaſes his power over his Miſtreſs by a long Apprentiſhip of ſervitude and compliance? Is it ſo that the ſame perſon by an happy contradiction is at once both dead and alive, and <hi>Phoenix</hi> like makes himſelf a <hi>vital</hi> funeral-pile, that he may revive more Nobly from his Flames? Is it ſo that there is ſo much madneſs and <hi>maliciouſneſs</hi> in the deſires of Lovers, as to wiſh them miſerable who are <note place="margin">At once malicious and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous.</note> moſt dear to them, only that they may have an opportunity to relieve their misfortune? Firſt to inflict a wound, that they may be the authors
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106094:13"/>
of its Cure? To wiſh them deſerted of their friends and fortune, that they may ſucceed in their Room? So that <hi>neceſſity</hi> rather than <hi>Courtſhip</hi> and <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> may allure them into their em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces? 'Tis hard to know whether you have to deal with a friend or an enemy, ſince the ſame part is thus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſly acted by hatred and too ardent affection. 'Tis ſomewhat unkindly done to deprecate the Love of others, that he himſelf may engroſs all, and to forbid and implead all other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions as encroaching on his pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar; nay more, ſtudiouſly to contrive how to prevent the growing wiſdom of his deareſt, leſt it ſhould occaſion a contempt of himſelf. For 'tis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient <note place="margin">No Love without ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation.</note> that the perſon <hi>lov'd,</hi> as well as the <hi>Lover</hi> be blind. How al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo does the feveriſh and love-ſick breaſt labour under the alternate Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roxyſms of heat and cold. Neither is there any Love without a mixture of indignation. He curſes (and that deſervedly too) his pleaſing tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor that ſcorches him in theſe flames, and ſnatches him from Himſelf; but ſtill like the fly he loves to ſport a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>dazling</hi> brightneſs, and from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106094:14"/>
ſo divine an Author to <hi>enjoy</hi> a Noble ruin.</p>
            <p>The unhappy Lover ſeeks for himſelf out of himſelf, and lingers on purpoſe to be caught, that he may have the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of redeeming himſelf, and knows no better way to be next to himſelf, than to approach as nigh as he can to the poſſeſſour of his heart. He finds it a difficult thing to Love, and much more not to Love, but the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt difficulty of all is to <hi>acquieſce</hi> in the fruition of his Love. He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be otherwiſe than miſerable, ſince the iſſue of his deſires is as uneaſie to him as the deſires themſelves: So that ſhould auſpicious Heaven favour him with a ſuccesful Love, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently wiſhes again for his former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiets, and ſeems to miſs that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Torment, to ſigh and languiſh. So much more pleaſant is it to be alwaies <hi>advancing</hi> toward an enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 'than to be <hi>lock'd up</hi> in the <hi>Chains</hi> of an embrace. And truly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one thinks more highly of his deſires, than of the accompliſhment of them. No condition certainly can make him happy, who pines at fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelf, as depriving him of his ſighs
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106094:14"/>
and penſive pleaſures. And this is the hard misfortune of all Lovers, who though never ſo much the favourites of fortune, yet can never be happy through the <hi>conſpiracy</hi> of their own minds.</p>
            <p>How ſtrange is it that he ſhould ſhun <note place="margin">He loves and fears the ſight of his belov'd.</note> the preſence of that perſon as ſome boding object, whoſe aſpect is yet the very <hi>Manna</hi> of his ſoul, and the raies of whoſe face he thinks more pleaſant than thoſe which ſaluted him at his Nativity! What a <hi>Paradox</hi> of unhappineſs is this to be maſter of ones wiſh, and yet not be able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it. Why 'tis that majeſtic beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which does at once invite and diſcourage, 'tis the brightneſs of that Serene face which like that of the Sun, does at once refreſh and dazle the beholder. The poor Votary ſtands aſtoniſh'd with the dread of ſo great divinity, which his own fancy has clothed with an awful horror; thunderſtruck like a <hi>Cyclops</hi> with bolts of his own forging. His paſſion has Deifi'd his Miſtreſs, ſo that now the enjoyment ſeems too great and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to be made uſe of, and he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins with a kind of envy to beome
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106094:15"/>
his <hi>own</hi> rival. A Religious concern aws him from Embraces, and the <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> of his Love whiſpers him in the ear, that what he takes for his Deity muſt not be approach'd with Corporal Addreſſes, but only by the <hi>Sallies</hi> of thought.</p>
            <p>Certainly this paſſion is favour'd with the peculiar care of Heaven, ſince it has mingled a melancholy trembling with its joys, only to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hance and refine the pleaſure. Hence 'tis that the deſires ſo torment, as <note place="margin">He rejoyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and ſighs by courſe.</note> that they alſo pleaſe, and the ſweets are ſo beſet with prickles, that they alſo allay our complacencies. They are ſparingly imparted to us, yet ſo as Ladies faces, which are only more <hi>openly</hi> hid through their thin ſilk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en veils. So that 'tis their fortune at once to have and want, ſince they aſpire at greater bliſs than can poſſibly be enjoy'd all at once. Theſe little <hi>antepaſts</hi> of Love, to ſit by, to walk with, to gaze upon, and to ſpeak to her, are permitted only one at a time. And after all this, the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing and reſtleſs mind, ſatisfi'd neither with gazing nor converſing, aſpires unto ſomething more divine,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106094:15"/>
which is both out of her reach and knowledge. This is (I know not by what deſtiny) this is the proper infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of Lovers, that becauſe they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver uſe to lay hold on any happineſs but in a dream, they <hi>Sceptically</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt their moſt real delights, treat them as tenderly as if they were dreams and ſhadows, refuſe to be impoſed upon again, and are <hi>afraid</hi> even to <hi>enjoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This very paſſion which compoſes all other commotions of the Mind, which civilizes Men, Brutes and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, is at variance only with it ſelf, and weds together things of an unlike nature in a jarring and untuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble union. Do you upbraid our <note place="margin">He is at once effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> Lover with Effeminacy, whoſe arms are fretted only with embraces: who always breathes out either perfumes or ſighs; who is ſtruck down with the menace of a ſleight frown, and the glance of an eye? Know that he is alſo hardy and maſculine, who can endure his careful Vigils, patiently expecting at the door all night for the day-break of his Miſtreſſes eyes, and exerciſing his mind with ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied repetition of cuſtomary hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106094:16"/>
till he become greedy of freſh encounters. He delights to ſupply the <hi>dearth</hi> of fears and troubles by his <hi>fruitful</hi> imagination, to turn the hazards of his health into ſo many ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments for his Love, the paleneſs of his complexion into a mode of Courtſhip, and by miſery it ſelf to <hi>demonſtrate</hi> himſelf a Lover.</p>
            <p>Do you call him ſtupid, becauſe he's as much affected and inflamed with blows and flouts as with the greateſt endearments of kindneſs? Believ't, he's become all Soul, or at leaſt a celeſtial ſpark of fire, which is inſenſible of ſtrokes; or if that ſound ridiculous, know that 'tis the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy of Love to conquer anger with kindneſs, and extinguiſh one fire with another, but a more noble one. This does notwithſtanding rather argue the great fervour, than ſtupidity of the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; for as injuries diſregarded wear off, ſo lovingly receiv'd are changed into favours; or as all hard things, are broken upon a <hi>yielding</hi> ſoftneſs.</p>
            <p>Why do you ſtill exclaim againſt <note place="margin">The faults of a Lover Pleaſe.</note> him as mad and blind, becauſe he dotes upon the very blemiſhes of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as ſtarry ornaments, collects a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106094:16"/>
beauty out of defects, and by a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natured miſtake, like a <hi>Panegyriſt,</hi> graces a fault with the name of a neighbour Vertue? Let his Miſtreſs be never ſo careleſs of her ſelf, the <hi>Artificial</hi> Lover ſtill repreſents her to himſelf in the moſt lively ornament of additionary Beauty. But you with too much rigour require a <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor</hi> inſtead of a <hi>Friend,</hi> and <hi>Judgement</hi> inſtead of <hi>Affection,</hi> by envying the Lover this happy deluſion wherein he ſo pleaſes himſelf. Let him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon himſelf this commendable cheat, and frame a more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Idea of her in his mind, whom he intends there to adore and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate with a more than ordinary devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Painters ſhould not draw Faces too <hi>Conſcientiouſly,</hi> but now and then beſtow a favourable ſtroke, <hi>flatter</hi> the Original, and ſo poliſh the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, till by its ſhining ſmoothneſs, it become a Looking-glaſs rather than a Picture.</p>
            <p>You miſtake, if you think the <note place="margin">Blind, but withal quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted.</note> Eyes of Lovers are blinded; no they are only mask'd, and ſo ſee the more clearly and ſecurely through their Avenues and Loop-holes. You may
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106094:17"/>
rather think them contracted, as the manner of Archers is, that they may take the ſurer aim. When they ſtand fix'd on one object, 'tis not through blindneſs that they ſee not the reſt, but a diſdainful and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary neglect. When the eyes weary themſelves with gazing on one ſingle object, and as 'twere of ſet purpoſe grow <hi>Bankrupt,</hi> and lay out their whole ſight upon it, that they may never ſee any thing beſides, this is not to be blind, but to ſee too much. If the entertainment of Philoſophy be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but to contemplate Idea's, ſure no employment ſo Philoſophical as to Love. Yea more, if every one Loves juſt as much as he underſtands, then what is counted the <hi>Madneſs</hi> of the affections, is indeed an argument of knowledge, to be vehemently Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick. Hear the Stratagems and Sieges of Lovers, equal to the Conqueſts over Kingdoms. Look upon the train of Captive Ladies, daily led in Triumph, as ſo many Living Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies of their Wit, who muſt firſt be <hi>deceiv'd,</hi> before they can be taken, and be brought <hi>unwillingly</hi> to what they deſire. So much would they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106094:17"/>
be wheedled than plainly lov'd, and be circumvented with wiles and ſubtilties, before they are with em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces. Think, if you can, what Enthuſiaſtic Strains are inſpired by a Miſtreſs, what an Itch of Poetry ſhe excites in the Paſſions of a Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Breaſt, and teaches it to make Wanton Sallies in Odes and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grams. Ambitious of ſuch an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſm, you will cry out with the Poet, <hi>O grant I may be in Love:</hi> And <note place="margin">Love has reaſon in its mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> over after invoke <hi>Cupid</hi> inſtead of <hi>Apollo.</hi> You maliciouſly err, whoever you are that take the myſteries of a Divine Ecſtaſie for the Wild Ranges of an Unhing'd Mind. Love does moſt luckily, without any Conſultation, diſpenſe his Motions, and with an un-erring Hand darts forth Humane Hearts, though Blind, and ſo not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of hitting the Mark by aim. For his Hand is directed not by the Eye, but ſome Divine Inſtinct, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is he ſteer'd by Reaſon, but acts by ſomewhat more Divine, like God himſelf, who is not endow'd with Reaſon, which would betray him into Error, but proſecutes whate're he does by a moſt Infallible tendency,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106094:18"/>
and owes not his Wiſdom to the <hi>Chain</hi> of Deliberation.</p>
            <p>How agreeably do theſe two things <note place="margin">'Tis pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to a wiſe man.</note> conſpire, to Know and to Love! Since it ſeems the Prerogative of God, and next to him of a Wiſe man, who knows, as certainly as the Oracle, who's beſt; for to Love any beſides the beſt is impoſſible. This is that only He, who paſſes a Judgement as even, and as true, as the Laws of Fate. He cannot be ſaid to Love, who is miſ-led by his opinion, and who makes an unſuitable choice; or which one time or other he muſt neceſſarily Hate.</p>
            <p>For the Union of Lovers knows no more how to admit of a Divorce, than the moſt Solemn Marriage. The Virginal Zone is no ſooner un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loos'd, but there ſucceds another Knot, which like the Gordian one, may perhaps be cut aſunder, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver unty'd: For although Death can do the former, yet it cannot the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The Love does not dye with its departed Object. His Conſort will not ſeem old to him, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſhe is, and that Spring of Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is now faded into an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106094:18"/>
will be kept in his faithful mind freſh and verdant; and he will Love with his <hi>memory</hi> at leaſt his now diſguiſed and almoſt unknown Wife. Nay never after the laſt ſeparation, his <note place="margin">Love is perpetual<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>ever, ever</hi> ſurviving friend ſhall live in his tenacious memory, as if he were divided from him only by the little intervals of abſence: And as often as he embraces his ſweet Phantaſm, he will not yield him dead. You do nothing, ye Fates, we ſtill continue our Commerce, we are ſtill a loving Couple; you have robb'd others of a man, but me not ſo much as of a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. Before we had but one Soul be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us, but now but one body. He is lodg'd in me as in his Star or Orb.</p>
            <p>And now Love ſeems to have made its Circle, always returning whence <note place="margin">It is a Circle,</note> it began, reſembling the motions of Heavenly bodies, it ſo ends in it ſelf that it always begins. For he is no Lover who can one time or other Love leſs or not at all. Love has not as other things any end or ſatiety, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it like hunger and thirſt to be allay'd by its aliment. It is never glutted with its gratifications, but is
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106094:19"/>
ſtill whetted on with freſh delights: and as if the object were alwaies new, the Lover enjoys a daily <hi>Epicuriſm</hi> on his admired face. There is a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſpring in his delights, a continual thirſt in his appetite, and he always finds out ſomething more to be fond of. He is always in motion like the heavenly bodies and a Contemplative mind, never reſts, never grows weary, but is refreſh'd by his labour. He makes the end of one kindneſs but a ſtep to another, till inflam'd with a double ardour, he firſt dotes on the perſon, and then on his own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits.</p>
            <p>'Tis neceſſary that Love be immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, <note place="margin">It is a death.</note> either becauſe 'tis vow'd to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, or becauſe it always under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goes the changes of death. For who is there that does not know that the laſt Will and death of a Lover muſt be dated from the time, when he breathes out his ſoul in his laſt ſigh to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the mouth of another, makes him compleat Heir of himſelf, diſpenſes his goods, ſending them before as har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingers, whither he is prepared to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low? He has the Divine priviledge of Prophets to be rapt out of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106094:19"/>
to enjoy a perpetual ecſtaſie of life, and to be emptied of his own Soul, that he may be more happily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſh'd <note place="margin">This is the Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorical Tranſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration.</note> with anothers. I believe the Tranſmigration of <hi>Pythagoras</hi> may be thus verifi'd, not by his <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> but by his <hi>Love.</hi> For then his deſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious and <hi>quickſilver</hi> ſoul ſhifting it ſelf at pleaſure of the bodily caſe as of Cloths, repairs haſtily to its plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanter retreat, and more fair recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle, as to the groves of <hi>Elyſium.</hi> No perſon can be happy before <hi>this</hi> death, which is occaſion'd by Love and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy. The latter does it by diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging the ſoul from the body, now all-diſſolving in the Contemplation of amiableneſs: The former, by ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it forth to the imbraces of its fair Object. Thence ariſes a loathing, hence a flight and riddance of himſelf. On each hand there is an aſpiring to a Fate Noble and void of all <hi>neceſſity,</hi> and Phoenix-like an ambitious longing for death. At the ſight of a more Elegant Structure, like a delicate and nice Lady, he nauſeates his own a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment with a <hi>proud</hi> uneaſineſs, and then wanders out into thoſe florid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, where ſince it was not his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106094:20"/>
to be born, he will ſojourn till he grow old in them, or by repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the rudiments of his life be <hi>re-born.</hi> Whoever you are who will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit theſe excurſions of fugitive ſouls, do but obſerve more narrowly how the ſoul collects it ſelf all to that place, where ſhe approaches neareſt to her deareſt. If they joyn hands, you'd ſwear their <hi>palpable</hi> ſouls diſtributed themſelves into the fingers on purpoſe to take faſt hold of each other. If their ſides be contiguous, you'l perceive an exultation of their hearts, and their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits mutually trooping thither in an hurry, violently beating, and like Ruſticks ſaluting one another with ſtrokes; ſtriving for vent, till they almoſt break Priſon to get forth. By what Charm is the ſuddain and <hi>Extempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Whence bluſhing proceeds from the ſight of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon lov'd.</note> blood fummon'd up into the Cheeks at the ſight of that dear Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and as the hand of a wounded heart <hi>points</hi> at the ſtriker, no otherwiſe than as the revengeful blood of a ſtain man vents it ſelf upon the Murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? With this only difference, that one of theſe Crimſon ſouls by I know no what inſtinct haſtens after Revenge, and the other after a Cure. Obſerve
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106094:20"/>
again how greedily their ſouls keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sentinel in the ears, lie at catch for words, and by and by turn themſelves into them; interchange Spirits while they hold Conference, and inform the very deſires which they utter. Obſerve again how their Souls in a perpetual Emanation gliding from <note place="margin">Whence a <hi>deliqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi>
               </note> their eyes, waſte themſelves in Paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate glances, and ſuffer many a faint ſwoon with gazing. 'Tis one and the ſame thing with Lovers, to ſpeak and expire, to ſee and dart themſelves out, to gaze and be transform'd into the Spectacle. So impatient is the whole man of departure, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he ſhifts himſelf into the eye, ſometimes into the ear; and lives on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>that</hi> part where he enjoys his Conſort. Thus Love teaches men a more <hi>Compendious</hi> knack of living, and makes them content like ſome Inſects with one only ſenſe. Yet this is not to maim the man, but to render him more Divine, by the fewneſs of Organs required to the Function of life.</p>
            <p>But that which occaſions a ſweet <note place="margin">It is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion of the ſoul.</note> detriment in the body, gives inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Soul. Which though
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106094:21"/>
formed for one breaſt, now diffuſing it ſelf by a kind of expanſion informs another, <hi>redoubling</hi> its life. She knows not in this confuſed <hi>Miſcellany</hi> of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, for which ſhe was at firſt made, ſo that in all Love there is improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Whoever Loves, becomes forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a number by himſelf. Like <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipheron</hi> he carrys about with him his <note place="margin">He diffuſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one into many.</note> daily Company, and enjoys his other ſelf as his mate, if that may be call'd a number which is computed with the ſame counter, which one only man diſtinguiſhes placed here and there by turns. It happens by a fruitful errour to Lovers as well as Drinkers, that all things appear double to them; but withall ſo double, as the eyes are, which have but one motion, one viſion. Here you may ſee two running into ſo <note place="margin">Out of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it makes one.</note> cloſe an Embrace, that they incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate and become one, and ſo <hi>loſe</hi> their Embraces in the undiſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able foldings of their arms. While after the lot of <hi>Salmacis</hi> 'tis the ſame that does deſire and is deſired, he knows not whether he more truly Loves or is belov'd, neither does he <hi>enjoy</hi> but is <hi>changed</hi> into his wiſh. Piſh, you put a trick upon me now
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106094:21"/>
               <hi>Cupid</hi> with your exceſs of Munificence, while you hide that within my breaſt, which I ſeek to embrace. You are too propitious, do ſomething of a contrary nature, that we may be two, that we may perceive our ſelves to be what we wiſh. 'Tis prejudicial to a Lover to enjoy too much. 'Tis pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial that he whom I would have my partner, ſhould be all one with my ſelf. Always thus to will and nill the ſame has no ſociety in 't, but much of a <hi>Ridiculous</hi> tediouſneſs. When we would <hi>conſult,</hi> we do but <hi>aſſent</hi> by courſe, and inſtead of being mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally officious, we are ridiculous to one another. Methinks I embrace a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow inſtead of a friend, which always preſſes me cloſe at the heels, and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates all my motions. Withdraw a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle from me, O my friend nearer to me than my ſelf, <hi>wiſh</hi> as <hi>well</hi> to me as you can, but prithee <hi>Love</hi> me a little leſs.</p>
            <p>But O what a profitable bill of exchange has this <hi>Cupid</hi> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer</hi> of hearts! Whence the ſame Plaſtic ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Cementing Souls which out of many makes one, diffuſes alſo one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many! So 'tis the ſame Unite which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106094:22"/>
uncapable by it ſelf of Computation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is yet the principle of number. So Multiplication and Addition belong to the ſame art. Neither do we think this a damage, but an advantage, and perhaps a greater, to have our ſtrength collected than extended at large. The more ſimple every thing is, the more perfect. To tranſcend the bounds of all ſpace and number is the property of God. Whatever is the beſt and chiefeſt muſt be one.</p>
            <p>And as Love is honour'd with the perfection of chiefeſt Unity, ſo is it with another, that of ſelf-communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. For whatever is perfect, has ſtill one way to become <hi>more</hi> ſo, and that is by diſtribution of its ſelf. 'Tis an addition to its own fulneſs, to Inrich and Impregnate others. Hence 'tis, that the generous mind born as it were a Common Patron to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and as prone to Love as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Love of all, invents a ſtrange kind of Liberality, to give <note place="margin">It is the firſt gift.</note> away it ſelf to another: Which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the only proper good a man has to beſtow, and <hi>Primitive</hi> Donative. All other things are Foreign; and come not within the encloſure of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106094:22"/>
property, which we can no more tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give than the Sun or Common air, and which we have ſcarce right to <hi>uſe;</hi> but are guilty of Rapin when we preſume to <hi>give</hi> them, as being the gifts of Heaven and fortune.</p>
            <p>Whoever Loves makes a nearer advance to a Deity, and therefore, God-like, is wholly intent on this one thing, to be beneficial. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they who are well diſpoſed in mind, as well as thoſe of healthy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, feel an ingenuous itch of Generating, that is of venting their thoughts, are ſtill under the Travail of the brain, and the <hi>Chaſte</hi> deſires of propagating vertue. There is in fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful minds as in quick-flowing fountains <note place="margin">It is a name of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulency not want.</note> a certain active principle and reſtleſs ſpirit, which always puſhes them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to effuſion. So far is Love from proceeding from indigence, that 'tis a word which denotes abundance, and greatly relieves the wants of nature: Unleſs you will call reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies themſelves diſeaſes, becauſe joyn'd with them. Why ſhould we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain <note place="margin">It is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce.</note> any more of the Illiberality of Nature, ſince ſhe has granted this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous way of Commerce to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106094:23"/>
wherein every one ſurrenders up himſelf and receives another (for in Love we don't laviſhly beſtow, but exchange our ſelves) and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in another is more excellent, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers into his own Repoſitory? He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herits anothers wealth, decks him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with ſuppoſititious endowments, and ſupplies his own defects out of anothers ſtore.</p>
            <p>But unleſs I am deceiv'd, there is <note place="margin">Not with a deſign, though Lot of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</note> no ſuch thing as Traffick and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize in Friendſhip: Neither is this Loves Motto, <hi>Love that you may be Belov'd.</hi> No we give freely, without any proſpect of Gain, all that we are to another, with a <hi>deſign</hi> of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication only, though with the <hi>Lot</hi> of an exchange. For what is more liberal than thoſe Patterns of Love, God and our Parents? Whoſe Kindneſſes exceeding all Gratitude, can only be Adored, never Repaid. Yet even there, where all endeavours of Reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation would be <hi>Impious,</hi> there is ſomething of return, ſince the Votary, at once the workmanſhip and maker of his God, does Deifie him by Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. And ſo he that owes the good of a ſhort Life to his Parents,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106094:23"/>
repays them with a <hi>Poſthumous</hi> one, being not ſo much the Inheritor as Preſerver of their tranſmitted Soul. See how the Vine, now no longer the Tree of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> but <hi>Cupid,</hi> ſurrounds her Maſculine prop with a thouſand Arms, and courts it with Amorous Embraces, that ſhe may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford the better Protection and Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to it for ſupporting her. She brings no other Encumbrances than her juicy Pearls, and refreſhing ſhades, whereby ſhe defends it from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities of Weather, which ſhe ſuſtains her ſelf. So that to ſpeak pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, Love does rather <hi>bring</hi> Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances than <hi>ſue</hi> for them. Whence it paſſes for a Badge of State, and becomes the part of Superiours to be more willing to Love, than to be Lov'd.</p>
            <p>Go now, you that think men are <note place="margin">Whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated from the rites of Love.</note> not Sociable out of a Principle of Benevolence, but that like the Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler ſort of Beaſts, they herd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ſuccour: Know that Love whom heretofore you took for a Boy, is long ſince grown up to maturity. Know that from theſe Altars is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed whatever is infirm, or of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106094:24"/>
worſer Sex, or of the weaker Age as barren Oblations, and Reproaches <hi>Profanely</hi> Pious. Neither may Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Women, Old men, or (what's more infirm than all theſe) one of an ill mind liſt themſelves under <hi>Cupid</hi>'s Banner. What an odd contention of Kindneſs will there be, where to Conquer, and to be Conquer'd are both full of ſhame, and Flight more creditable than either? What kind of League or Society can there be among thoſe, who have nothing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon but this <hi>one</hi> thing, <hi>to live?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what ſhall we ſay of that toyiſh <note place="margin">Children are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mature as for Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues ſo for Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> and impertinent Age, which changes Companions as often as Play-games, hourly; which is pleas'd with humane ſhapes in Arras as fine Company, but is affrighted with real men; whoſe unacquaintance with the cauſes of Love and Hatred is the merit of its Innocence, and a Vertue deſerving pity. Which becauſe it deals its affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to all as Parents, claims a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents Indulgency from all, not yet ripe for Friendſhip. Although even this pretty erring Benevolence may ſeem the <hi>Rudiments</hi> of Kindneſs, and the <hi>Nonage</hi> of Friendſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:106094:24"/>
What of that other too ſevere Age, <note place="margin">Old men alſo, who are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome either through too much dotage or too much ſageneſs.</note> not leſs troubleſome to others than to it ſelf? That age I mean, which only dotes upon a Staff, or if on a man, 'tis for the ſame end, that it may have ſomething to lean on. Which falls out with another at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fit of the Gout, and querulouſly blames the poor Lover for what is its own diſeaſe. Which with a mind as tremulous as Body ſuſpects every thing, which ſtands upon the Guard even at the offices of kindneſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as at the Arts of Infinuation. To be too officious in pleaſing the Man of this ſeaſon, is to anoint the dead. He always envies me the freedom of my youth, or corrects it by the Pattern of his own that's paſt, always nibling at my Manners, that he may oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely boaſt his own, and ſo becomes too much my Rival. One would think him dead ſometimes, to hear him talk of his Chronicles, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſing his old Epitaphs. I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually plagu'd with his rugged Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, no leſs than with his Jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and Snarlings, and all on this ſcore, becauſe I do not grow old faſt enough to dye with him for company.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106094:25"/>
He importunately urges me to reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him in his <hi>wrinkled</hi> ſeverity, and that <hi>Vertue,</hi> ſhall I call it, or <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> of old age? <hi>To be Wiſe and Moroſe.</hi> Methinks I ſtand preſented before a Magiſtrate, and am under a <hi>Cenſure,</hi> not a League of <hi>Society.</hi> But what more Cruel <hi>Mezentius</hi> is this, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troths Carkaſes to warm Embraces? And in the <hi>Jubilee</hi> of a Sprightly Life enjoins Dotage and Counſel? What unreaſonable Controller is this who commands me to live backward with a man of another Age? Whom to be Familiar with, is indecent, and whom to reverence at a diſtance, is to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonize</hi> him above the confines of Love and Humanity. But as the pleaſure of ſorting with equals, gives young minds an early foretaſte of a more mature Love; ſo it may ſeem the laſt effort of a decay'd heat, either out of Complaiſance to accommodate their dotage to the ſcandal of youth, or to Cough in conſort with thoſe of the ſame Age, and to enjoy at once the Remembrance and Envy of their paſt Amours. For they have nothing now to do (having with much regret receiv'd their <hi>Mittimus)</hi> but to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106094:25"/>
at others Loves, to miniſter to others the <hi>Philtres</hi> of Advice, and to ſigh, to teach them ſoft Embraces, and to languiſh for the deſire of them. For theſe Mortify'd Skeletons ſtill mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably pant with the Relicts of their Flames as of their Lives, which do not inſpirit them with any preſent vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacity, but rather ſhew they did once live, and ſo apply the Marriage-Torch of <hi>Cupid</hi> to the Pomp of a Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</p>
            <p>But, O <hi>Cupid,</hi> O <hi>Hymen!</hi> What <note place="margin">Women alſo as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimals of a different kind from Man.</note> unequal Torches do you kindle? A Man with a Woman! This is not to unite, but to deſtroy. Theſe are a couple more unhappily match'd than the Soul with the Body; whoſe Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, while it gratifies her, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grades and diſhonours her, and in a pretence to ſerve, cheats and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices her. There's ſo much diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, that a Woman can't fill the other Scale of the Ballance without additionary Gold. There's need of a Dowry and ſtipend to theſe Embraces, theſe Careſſes. This is a Felicity to be bought, we don't admit you to it <hi>gratis.</hi> Neither is a Woman to be eſteem'd a <hi>Conſort</hi> to a man, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106094:26"/>
to the <hi>Inventory</hi> of his <hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Chattels;</hi> the furniture of his Bed-Chamber, and the Ornament of his Table. She ſerves inſtead of a little Shock to divert ones ſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, not to employ any part of ones life about. She ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded only at thoſe dull hours, which nature has allotted for grief and ſleep. My Miſtreſs is welcome at Supper-time or at Night, that time I'll throw away on her which would be loſt otherwiſe. She can ſcarce fill up theſe <hi>Intervals</hi> of life, theſe <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentheſis</hi>'s of reſpite, and little <hi>blanks</hi> of action. She is added to the tasks of rigorous nature, and helps on the loſs of our time, more than eating and ſleeping. Shall I call this a Wife? By the leave of the Female Academy I'll tell you plainly what I think. I believe theſe <hi>Expletive</hi> Particles of mankind were put into the world for no other end than flyes, only to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a vacancy. I ever took this fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous Impertinent to be a certain middle Animal, which like a Centaur compounds a man with a Beaſt, and detains him as it were within the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of both natures and a Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſis.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106094:26"/>
Will you call this Society, whereby a man gains this <hi>one</hi> thing, not to be <hi>alone?</hi> 'Tis more than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for them if they can but own the force of reaſon and ſubmit to it, though they never uſe any, and like Creatures naturally Wild and Savage, can be made tame and civiliz'd by familiarity. There's nothing in them deſerves ſo much Caution, as leſt they ſhould grow wiſe, or know any thing beyond bare ſilence, and the <hi>ſimplicity</hi> of pleaſing.</p>
            <p>Friendſhip is too Sacred a thing to admit of any Embraces, though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, <note place="margin">Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is a work of reaſon as well as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</note> which it ought to bluſh at if obſerv'd. 'Tis a flame too Noble to be attended with any levity, nay 'tis a Marriage too ſtrait to a dmit any difference of Sex. This is the higheſt <note place="margin">Which only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with it ſelf and makes two live by one rule.</note> work of reaſon to make choice of ſuch a perſon, whoſe conduct you would rather uſe than your own, to whoſe will you would always conform; or even to know how to wait ſo long, till you can chooſe a fit object for your Love, and after that ſo to Love as one that's hurri'd with bare Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, not ſteer'd with judgment, as one that's ſo far from Apoſtaſie that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106094:27"/>
he is always beginning his Love. This is to joyn impatience with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy. This is to receive the belov'd Idea imprinted in the mind with more exactneſs, and to retain it with more faithfulneſs than Wax. Beſides, 'tis alſo the work of vertue to ſtate one <note place="margin">It is a work of vertue.</note> meaſure of deſires, to preſerve an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act uniformity of manners through all the various ſcenes of fortune, and laſtly ſo to Harmonize two, that (what <hi>one</hi> can hardly perform) they may act <hi>one</hi> man. Theſe muſt of neceſſity always will the ſame, becauſe they will only the beſt things. There muſt <note place="margin">Whoſe Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is without deteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> needs be alſo between them the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt freedom of Communion, becauſe they communicate what without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy they poſſeſs, their Vertues; and ſo with greedineſs they <hi>Covet</hi> an effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of theſe goods of their mind, till the Candor of their Souls like the light of Heaven improve it ſelf by an inceſſant Emanation. Add to this, that the League of this rational friendſhip will be firmer than the Stoical Chain of Deſtiny, ſince the perpetual alliance of Souls is not here founded upon having the ſame Parents, but the ſame prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of living, reaſon, and (what
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106094:27"/>
has a more Vital influence) the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing endued with the deſire of the ſame excellency rather than with the ſame blood. The having the breaſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pant with the ſame deſires, than the Arteries beat with the ſame ſpirits. The having a ſhare in the ſame good and bad fortune, a more indearing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance than a common off-ſpring. You come ſhort of the myſtery, if you think the ſame ſoul, or the ſamedivided reſides in two bodies, 'tis more, they have the ſame Soul in two bodies <hi>one</hi> and <hi>uniform.</hi> You'd think even the <hi>envy</hi> of thought could not abſtract them, ſince there is nothing left to diſtinguiſh them. For whatever diſtinguiſhes would at length divide them, nay 'twou'd make them conceive a greater diſguſt againſt each other like Half-brothers from the very nearneſs.</p>
            <p>In vain are friendſhips and allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as all other Vertues pretended to <note place="margin">An ill man is not a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable Creature.</note> by Vicious men: Who are provok'd to mutual hatred and animoſity by having the ſame pleaſures, as much as by having the ſame Miſtreſſes. To have the ſame thing commodious to both (though this be ſomewhat more Divine than to have the ſame common
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106094:28"/>
parents) breeds envy from their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky fellowſhip, and quarrels greater than thoſe of mutual Pillagers, birds of prey or Coheirs. No third per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will envy, but wonder at their conjunction, nay and will hardly grant <note place="margin">He diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with himſelf, avoids himſelf.</note> them joyn'd any otherwiſe than fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſailers in the ſame bottom, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to each other by fears and dangers; whom aſſoon as Landed the ſucceſs of the voyage will diſingage, whoſe ſociety will ſuffer Shipwrack <note place="margin">He is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to Society, not out of benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence but ſelf-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain.</note> from the Land-tempeſt of Intereſt and Traffick, and be diſſipated into va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Climes by the greater Love of Countries than of men. With what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy can you think they will adhere to others, who were not mov'd to this Sociable humour from a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of benevolence, but a great wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs of themſelves? They can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">They who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure thoſe of like or unlike manners, like ulcers avoid the touch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the Surgeon.</note> endure the <hi>Penance</hi> of their own Company, and therefore ſtrive to loſe themſelves among Crouds, not uſing the nicety of Choice, but catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the firſt opportunity of refuge. For who can pleaſe them who don't like themſelves, who abhor the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of unſpotted Morality as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like their own actions, and upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106094:28"/>
of them, and therefore dread them as Malefactors do the Magiſtrate? And as for actions reſembling their own (ſo great is their fear to be try'd even by imitation) they put from them as Rivals to prevent their own extruſion, and fly them as deformity do's a Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. This is the firſt puniſhment of immorality, by its own ſentence even amongſt men to be adjudg'd to the worſt kind of ſolitude, treacherous Society. 'Tis the fate of an ill man to do all this in vain; To cheapen the good-will of others with a <hi>Tale</hi> of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, to let his mercenary ſoul for a little Hire and fair words, diligently to attend his friends, yet ſo as he cleanſes ſhoes, and rubs down his Horſe as things ſerviceable and belonging to his Eſtate; in fine, to do all this only for his own ends, and (which is the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Fate of great benefactions) to loſe all through ingratitude, and among theſe amorous addreſſes to fortune, to burn with an hatred and loathing of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Would any one now joyn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to him <hi>another</hi> ſelf, whom he ſees thus diſagreeing with himſelf? Would any one be ambitious of his <hi>Cruel</hi> benevolence, by whom he would
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106094:29"/>
not be lov'd with the ſame mind wherewith he ſtands affected to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? Whoſe ſerene looks like thoſe of <hi>Mars</hi> and Fortune, he muſt be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of, and enjoy his delights as ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merouſly as Treacheries, or ſuch which the next blaſt or Sunſhine will ſcatter or diſſolve. Methinks I ſee the ill match'd pair exactly reſembling a ſpread Eagle, with ſtriving Embraces, like faces, both averſe from each other as in a Divorce, contrary tendencies, always avoiding and always pulling one another back. Diſſolve ye Gods this unhappy, this forced connexion, and ye Painters the bolder Artificers. Half of the Monſter will flee away and deſert it ſelf, and then 'twill appear they ſtumbl'd upon one another by error, not met out of choice. O deform'd Prodigy of <hi>Venus!</hi> Nature abhors theſe Inceſtuous Conjunctions more than the Monſtrous productions of Creatures of a ſeveral kind. Nothing is more unhappy than this ſort of Lovers, who like the Emperors of Old time, or like birds, betroth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves here and there at random, but on a ſet time, and with due Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and yet preſently after the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106094:29"/>
ſeaſon is over diſingage again. When the heat is abated there enſues a new ardour of Divorce. Their affection endures no longer than the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived guſt of the Banquet, when they are ſatiated they muſt riſe. For they don't know all the while what'tis which they Paſſionatly long'd for. Their caſual affection ſprings from the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their deſires, like <hi>Venus</hi> from that of the Waves. 'Tis cheriſh'd and kept alive by miſtakes, and no ſooner throughly known than diſapprov'd. To ſpeak freely, whoever Love through Brute tendency or diſeaſes, do rather burn and rave together in a <hi>Fever,</hi> than conſent in the Harmony of <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is enacted by the ſevere Statute-Law of Nature as well as the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict <note place="margin">The Law of <hi>Lycur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> and Nature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, in making it a Crime to Love no body.</note> of <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> not for the Luxury but Diſcipline of the world, that no man ſhall be without his Lover. How well is it, that there is the ſame neceſſity impos'd upon us of Loving and living, and that the ſame radical heat proves <hi>Amorous,</hi> as well as <hi>Vital!</hi> The <hi>Epicureans</hi> who could be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without the protection of the Gods, could not yet endure to be
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106094:30"/>
without Love whom they might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore, and in whoſe Religion they might more ſweetly entertain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. So much more willing are we to make our own Deities, than to <note place="margin">You may ſooner find an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt than and philiſt.</note> receive them made to our hands. And becauſe 'tis Natural to us to be actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated by the inſtinct of Love and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, we uſe the ſame zeal of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition in both, and rather than want an Idol to adore, we adopt the moſt unworthy and ridiculous things, Cats and Dogs, and whatſoever was Idoliz'd in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> into the liſt of our friends and Houſe-hold-gods. Nay ſo great is the impatience of Love, that the poor homely <hi>Gellia</hi> for want of better ſervants makes a Gallant of her Looking glaſs, and what <hi>Aegypt</hi> would be aſham'd of, adores a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more Monſtrous than any of <hi>Nile, herſelf.</hi> But 'tis a venial ſin, we are all guilty of the ſame madneſs, and would rather doat fooliſhly, than Love nothing. Whether you will or nill, you muſt neceſſarily will ſomething, ſince in your very nilling ſomething is deſired. The reſt indeed of our <note place="margin">There is no man who is not</note> Paſſions are diſpoſed of at our pleaſure, or elſe eaſily dwindle away conſumed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106094:30"/>
by their own violence. Grief if it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe <note place="margin">free ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from the other Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</note> to yield to reaſon, yields at length to time, to hatred. Hatred through the diſturbance of Choler or fear becomes troubleſome, firſt to it ſelf. And fear, not to mention any other remedy, may be cruſh'd by the evils themſelves, and overcome by its own greatneſs harder, and be cured by Stupidity. Anger the moſt impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of all, either by wearineſs is tamed into Clemency, or being ſatiated dies, leaving like the Bee its life in the wound. This one Paſſion which <note place="margin">None was ever free from Love.</note> grows Luxuriant in croſſes, and Bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms more deliciouſly under preſſures, not given to us as the reſt were, to be ſubdu'd; grows up into a neceſſity and <hi>Voluntary</hi> Fate. It freely parted with its liberty, which it quite ſpent in the election of that, which with an immortal deſire it might at once poſſeſs and proſecute: Which it might wiſh never to have the power to hate. And now <hi>what Modeſty</hi> or <hi>meaſure is there in deſire?</hi> Whoſe Efforts if at <note place="margin">Love knows no meaſure becauſe it aſpires to the beſt.</note> any time miſplaced, yet at leaſt with a generous error they aſpire to all as the moſt excellent objects. Of which he is unworthy who is not arrived
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106094:31"/>
to this <hi>Hyperbole</hi> of madneſs, ſtill more and more to deſire, and yet to think he deſires not enough; ſtill more and more to enjoy, and yet not to be content with enjoyment, and to careſs himſelf in his ever <hi>unſatisfying</hi> happineſs.</p>
            <p>So 'tis: The Author of Nature <note place="margin">As 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to Love no body, ſo it is to Love one who is not beſt.</note> hath by a firm Law, made it equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impoſſible either to Love none, or not the beſt. The former of which is with an inhumane pride to vilifie mankind, and the latter by the worſt of Parricides, to deſtroy a mans ſelf. For when he had the option of life given him, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal of his Nativity put into his own hands, and could have <hi>re-made</hi> himſelf in another, yet he choſe to Periſh. The Monarchy of the breaſt like that of <hi>Alexander,</hi> muſt be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to the beſt deſerving, whom to find ſhould be the buſineſs of ones life. It muſt be a man made up of the higheſt endowments incident to Mortality, as compleat as a <hi>Woman</hi> 
               <note place="margin">That beſt which is no where in nature we ſupply by opinion, and ſo patch up a feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city out of variety.</note> could wiſh. A <hi>Catholick</hi> man accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106094:31"/>
with all the <hi>Hyperbole</hi> of vertues which may be any where found or imagin'd, and of which a man may have a notion, never the poſſeſſion. In a word ſuch a man, whom when with <hi>impious</hi> deſires we have form'd, 'tis an Idea, or a God. And now alas! we find his dignity ſomething a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove our Love, and fit only to be adored; worthy indeed of our Love but much more of our adoration. Theſe are the flames due to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar. Nature has implanted this deſire in us to her own diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being not able to fill it. But yet leſt what ſhe intended as her greateſt favour ſhould prove a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (ſuch as always provokes and never ſatisfies) ſhe has ſo order'd it, that what is wanting in the things themſelves ſhould be ſupplied by our opinion, that our miſtake at leaſt might make up our happineſs. We are gull'd with a counterfeit dreſs of Beauty, and are firſt deceiv'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are conſcious of any happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Like <hi>Pigmalion</hi> we fall in Love with a Statue of our own making, and then think its Beauty not artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial but native. The miſt of our ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106094:32"/>
recommends a cloud to our greedy Embraces inſtead of <hi>Juno,</hi> nay we Love to be cheated, and think it a part of humanity to be liable to ſlips, errors and miſpriſions. We are not damaged but gratifi'd in our deſires by this <hi>profitable</hi> impoſture, ſince the cheat pleaſes us more than the jugling ſhifts of Legerdemain, and inriches us with no falſe appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of gain. Our credulity makes us truly happy, and (what is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lot of men of great Eſtates) we become more rich by the fame and ſuſpicion of Wealth, than the largeneſs of our fortune. Go then enjoy ſecurely thoſe Treaſures which you owe to the kindneſs of fancy, not to the bounty of providence; Thoſe moſt fortunate collations not of a ſmiling fortune, but of an obliging opinion; thoſe goodly poſſeſſions, which neither when the Gods frown, nor when fortune is diſpos'd to be wantonly miſchievous, are liable to danger. Which no violence, no nor another opinion will ſnatch away, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to give a new ſupply. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though opinion as the Siſter of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune or Nature be pleas'd with vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106094:32"/>
yet the Love of variety will not <note place="margin">Hence the levity of Loving is a remedy to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of things.</note> recommend Monſters to her. She is not wanton to that pitch of levity, but only redreſſes the defects of things. The viciſſitudes and changes of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections like thoſe of things are ſet out not ſo much for Beauty, as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace and remedy. We reprehend the wandring and Alternate heat of Love to the diſcredit of Nature, not of thoſe men who daily caſt off their Thred bare Companions like old ſutes, who take a deſultorious taſt of men as Bees do of Flowers, and becauſe good is always to them in flux and uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as truth is to Philoſophers, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to Love <hi>ſceptically:</hi> Neither is it an Argument of inconſtancy, but judgment, thus to wander with choice, and to collect that from all in various <note place="margin">'Tis a ſign of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and choice.</note> 
               <hi>Gleanings,</hi> which is in no one place to be had enough. No one thing is worthy long enjoyment; and theſe ſhadows of vertues rather than real ones, which we ſo much boaſt of, like rich Pictures endure only a curſory view at a diſtance, cannot bear the delay of nice obſervation, and vaniſh while leiſurely beheld. All that's in that Pompous Title of Conſtancy
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106094:33"/>
is not of ſuch moment, that I ſhould not do Homage to a greater merit, that I ſhould not prefer a brighter Star, becauſe once born under an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurer Planet, that I ſhould obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adhere to defects and loſſes, left I ſhould be ſaid to have departed from my firſt condition; or laſtly that I ſhould endure my chance, or what is altogether as erroneous, my own will, as calmly and immoveably as I would my deſtiny. Give me leave I pray, more paſſionately to admire thoſe Rays of a diviner mind which I firſt adored in you, now more Brightly Shining in another. Suffer the progreſſes of Love which you firſt taught me. The ſame you who at firſt taught me to prefer the candor of your mind before the whiteneſs of <hi>Lillies</hi> or faces, and a rude ſimplicity before the enough eaſie, but fooliſh and too fond humanity, have now alſo taught me after the ſight of a more Dazling Splendor to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn your ſelf, unleſs I may not hence be ſo properly ſaid to contemn, as adore you with more devotion under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> more glorious repreſentation. Juſt ſo the leſſer Lamps of Heaven are not extinct but over ſhadow'd, when
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106094:33"/>
out of modeſty they withdraw at the appearance of a greater Glory. Why do you call out upon the truth of Gods and men? I Love you only on this condition, ſo long as you either <hi>are,</hi> or to me <hi>ſeem</hi> the beſt.</p>
            <p>Do but look down upon the brute <note place="margin">All appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, even the moſt inſenſate tends to a better na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as to its Idea.</note> Love ſports of Nature (though 'tis a ſhame to owe the Documents of life and vertue to ſuch low inſtances) and ſee how all the parts even the worſt in the Divine workmanſhip have an innate tendency to what is beſt, and are carried with admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and deſire to a greater excellency. 'Tis purpoſely ſo order'd by Nature, who is conſcious of her own injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſhameful ſloth, who oftner ſuffers abortion than brings forth, and in Compariſon to the exemplars and Ideas of things is deliver'd of as many Monſters as Creatures. She has therefore indued them with a plaſtick vertue, that they may advance near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to their Ideas, and ſo become their own Correctors. Her work comes at firſt out of her hands in half and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect pieces, till ſhe joyns one part to another and ſo compleats both. This one ambition of aſpiring to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106094:34"/>
ſomething better, moves every thing to leap the <hi>Pale</hi> of its own condition. For this reaſon the <hi>Heliotrope</hi> though rooted faſt in the gound, follows the Courſe of the Sun, and with an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite mouth drinks in the Sun beams tell ſhe her ſelf become a <hi>Vegetable</hi> Star. <note place="margin">The double end of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Love.</note> With the ſame Ardour of ambition, while ſtones receive the Aethereal rays, they become a glittering concretion of <hi>Maſſy</hi> light, and what before were only the rigid Excreſcencies of a cragged bulk; now look like gems, and dart forth glimmerings as well in a Rock, as in a Lovers Ring. With this ſweet art while the Sea partakes as clearly of the motion as the image of the Moon, it enjoys the intelligence of the Celeſtial Orb as its own. With this lovely envy while the Steel is drawn with admiration of the Load ſtone, and by and by with mutual breathings and Nuptial Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces exhales its pretious Soul, as if 'twere now it ſelf become a Load-ſtone exerciſes Charms of its own, and draws other things as much as 'tis drawn it ſelf. There is indeed in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as well as in common life an ambitious indigency, and cringing to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106094:34"/>
Superiours. Neither is there any thing more regarded in another than the eminency of its order. Had we no ſuch thing as a Philoſopher, yet we have <hi>Philomathematical</hi> Waves, which ſhew the wain of the Moon with more certainty than Almanacks and Ephemerides. We have <hi>Aſtronomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Flowers, which teach us the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sun, and inſtead of ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king watches, give an Articular no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the declining day. Had this Theater of the World no Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſpectator, to conſider its rarities with Scrutiny and Inſpection, yet all Nature her ſelf is inamour'd to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with her own Beauty, and as both the eyes of the World, ſo both Worlds ſpeculate each other by courſe, and feed themſelves with mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual interviews. And this lower ſeems to aſpire to the dignity of the higher with the ſame ambition as is uſed by the commonalty of <hi>Spain,</hi> when they Emulate the Grandieur of the Nobility; and with the ſame art which the Commons of <hi>Rome</hi> uſed, when the <hi>Plebeians</hi> were admitted to match among the <hi>Patricians.</hi> The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Nature has made the welfare of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106094:35"/>
things too much his concern by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting <note place="margin">Beſides theſe there is a farther end of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in man, divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Eternity.</note> the world to the Tuition of Love, ſo that now an idle and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active Deity, will either not be own'd or contemn'd.</p>
            <p>But whereas other things are of ſuch a compoſure that they can only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and want, man alone knows how to Love. Nature has ſhadow'd forth in them a rude ſemblance of affection, only that ſhe might make a preluſory ſpecimen of that in viler materials, which ſhe intended to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat in man with Elaborate Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy. Although I muſt alſo acknowledge that the affections of men leiſurely improve according to the ſame degrees and proportions as they themſelves do, and as if they had ſeveral births, are firſt endow'd with life, then with ſenſe, and at laſt with reaſon; and that Love which is at firſt <hi>callow</hi> and creeps by the inſtinct of Occult ſympathy, by and by is <hi>Fledged</hi> with deſire, and at laſt improves into hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, and reaſon, which was before only Brute tendency, or the predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant bias of an Element. For when the as yet tender warmth only <hi>broods</hi> on the breaſt, much leſs has <hi>hatch'd</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:106094:35"/>
the glowing ſparks, the deſire ſcarce gives credit to it ſelf. When the <note place="margin">The vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and ages of all Loves.</note> mind is newly ſmitten, and is hardly yet Conſcious either of the wound or the Author of it; ſhe feels juſt ſuch <hi>innocent</hi> prickings as Children do from the Rupture of their Gums, when they breed Teeth. Then you may ſee a pretty ſpecimen of Infant ſimplicity, thoſe who have been born ſcarce long enough to view one another a little, beginning to ſigh together as one <hi>Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le-tree</hi> whiſpers to another. For in theſe early expreſſes of Paſſion theſe Infant Lovers don't underſtand the Air which they ventilate in the groves of <hi>Venus,</hi> while they wind Embraces inſenſibly, and like thoſe who lazily ſtretch themſelves, naturally ſeek out for ſomething to reſt their extended arms on. You may now if you will call theſe the inſinuating arms of an <hi>Ivy,</hi> or the winding branches of a Vine. But aſſoon as they improve their Love ſo far as to imprint and devour ſmacking Embraces, you don't ſee men but Ring-Doves. When they breath out their querulous A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours in wanton chidings, you hear Turtles, as being now a little more
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106094:36"/>
by Nature diſpoſed to benevolence, ſo that they affect others with ſweet and innocent fondneſs, and imitate the kindneſs of the <hi>Dolphin,</hi> or <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard.</hi> But men of an <hi>adult</hi> Flame are ſeiz'd with a more generous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe though blind. By this blind im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe we are carried upwards like Doves of <hi>Venus</hi> with ſeal'd eyes, and with a moſt vigorous endeavour ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly aſpire to Heaven as to a Neſt. Thus the very defects of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <note place="margin">The kinds of Baſtard Love and errors of Lovers</note> ſhew a diſpoſition greedy of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, and the errours of this one Paſſion aſpire to ſomething immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. So that even that more impure itch, which derides the <hi>Barren</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of Vertues and <hi>Copulations</hi> of Souls, which ſeeks ſomething to <hi>fill</hi> its Embraces, and adores the Planet <hi>Venus</hi> though threatning its birth-day with Storms and Shipwracks of life, ſeems yet to be inflamed not ſo much with the Torches of Hymen, as with the deſire of Eternity. While with ſuch Ardency it longs to out-live it ſelf, and by a long ſeries of poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to patch up as well as it can a <hi>ſucceſſive</hi> immortality. Even he whoſe friendſhip is purchas'd with a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106094:36"/>
a ſupper, whom like a Brute Creature a bit does befriend to you, who is in Love with your Kitchin not your ſelf, though he Loves to the proportion of his ſtomach: And he who values a <note place="margin">Even they who Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiate in the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aſpire to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</note> man after the ſame rate as he does a farm, attending on him with the ſame ſordid expectation as he does on his field, who uſes his friendſhip as a thing of profit with a mercenary mind, and ſtill reckons <hi>himſelf</hi> among his friendſhips: Why this latter well skill'd in the value of Love uſes it as money, but as a Divine Coin, wherewith we men Negotiate with the Gods, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich our ſelves with a Deity. And the former enjoys his Love to Luxury and Banquet, for he thinks it the Nectar of his Supreme Deity, as well as of <hi>Venus.</hi> Both of them truly with leſs Covetouſneſs conſult their own profit, either he that ſeeks a Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony <note place="margin">They are more libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral who do good of their own accord.</note> by his affection, or he that diets upon it, than he who haſtily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charges his ſinking Ship of her <hi>peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing</hi> fraught, and by a free disburſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his goods transfers them out of the reach of Chance or Fate before they periſh. Who although he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects no returns, nor ſells his gifts,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106094:37"/>
yet has already receiv'd a moſt am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple recompence, the very Collation of a kindneſs, and although he has given never ſo much, yet has laid up a greater Treaſure for himſelf, the Vertue of beneficence. So that to give great largeſſes, and ſuch as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty oftentimes forbids to receive, does the moſt advantage to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; either by rendring him awful, that nothing mean will be expected from him, or by repreſenting the benefit more neceſſary and natural than either Rain or Sun-ſhine. So that from him as from the Sun benefits will be exacted as Debts, and he will ſeem to do only according to Cuſtom and Duty, as often as he acts generouſly, ſo that all gratitude will be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way through the frequency and ample<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Collations.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I think of him who ſeeks to pleaſe, not to Love me? Whom I repair to as a Summer-bower, that may afford me ſhade and ſecurity, but which is of no uſe to me in the rage of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Whom as many of us as have any ſeverity mixt with our Loves are wont to Alarm with this grave: Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegm, <hi>A friend as a Wife, is a word
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106094:37"/>
of Dignity not of pleaſure.</hi> You have <note place="margin">Friend and Wife are names of honour.</note> found out a new way of being Libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinous without Embraces, you have deflowred your Love with this kind of Laſciviouſneſs, worſe than that of the ſtews. Induſtriouſly to pleaſe is the trick of wheedlers, and the lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious venom of a Pander. To treat too daintily, is a kind of ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: To fawn with emulous offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is like a Wooer, and belongs rather to the rudiments of Love than the life of Lovers. Far be't that you ſhould take that <hi>Creature</hi> for a friend, who is a torment to you while you deſire him, and a tediouſneſs when you poſſeſs him. And yet you are not much out, if you think that all Lovers wander in the fields of <hi>Elyſium,</hi> and that Flowers ſpring up where ever they tread. No other are the joys of Heaven than to Love and to be lov'd, no other are the joys of Earth. That Divine <hi>Ardor</hi> which makes the <hi>Empyreal</hi> Heaven to be what it is, and wherein will conſiſt the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the future life, muſt be the only Solace of this. In all other things we are Paſſive, theſe we only enjoy and delight in which are the Iſſues of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:106094:38"/>
our deſire and choice, and which in thoſe <note place="margin">There is no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where but from Love</note> other uneaſineſſes divert our pain. Thus have we ſeen in a Tempeſt the two Brothers rejoyce in a greedy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, bringing as much joy to them ſelves as to the Mariners, Congratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their united beams, whereby they loſe each other in a mutual embrace, and thence become two again. Thus have we known the Votaries of <hi>Venus</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with a Cloud, brought like Brides under a Veil of ſilk with more ſecret triumph to their joys. We confeſs there is ſomething in Love more powerful than calamities, more magnificent than honour, more ſplendid than Riches, more charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than pleaſures, for whoſe ſake we contemn all theſe, yea for whoſe ſake we do not contemn them, but have them in the greater veneration. It does ſo ſolely pleaſe, that by it all things elſe though never ſo vile pleaſe exceedingly. It has ſuch a priviledge of Majeſty that nothing can diſparage it, that it clears from infamy, and ſooner reflects a luſtre on the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt reproaches of life, than it can be ſullied from any thing elſe. Hence 'twas that this was added a thirteenth
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106094:38"/>
to the labours of <hi>Hercules,</hi> and ſerv'd as an ingredient to make up his praiſes, that he not only brandiſh'd his Club, but held a Diſtaff, with which (though he had tam'd all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wild Beaſts) yet one Monſter ſtill remain'd to be ſubdued, whom only the inſtruments of her own Arts can Conquer, <hi>a Woman.</hi> Why do you wonder ſo much at the inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Rays of the Sun, ſince <hi>Cupids</hi> Torch can alſo enlighten even the moſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did things, and yet remain untain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</p>
            <p>Why then does the hunger bitten mind ſo eagerly and to no purpoſe hunt after ſomething Divine in other things, ſince it has it at home? For indeed whatſoever we Love, is to us a Deity. <hi>Whatſoever you deſire that</hi>'s <hi>Jupiter.</hi> Is it ſo? What does that ſordid Lover who admits no conſort without a Dowry, kiſs, buy and count <hi>Jupiter</hi> imprinted on his Money? Yes, but 'tis <hi>Jupiter</hi> ſhining under a covert of Gold. What, and does the Libidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous voluptuary itch after <hi>Jupiter?</hi> Yes, but 'tis <hi>Jupiter</hi> turn'd Stallion under the form of a Satyr, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into the Semeleian flames. Yes
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:106094:39"/>
and ſo does that delicate Trencher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend ſup upon <hi>Jupiter,</hi> but in the ſhape of a Swan, and lurking under the ſoft <hi>Down</hi> of Luxury. He luſts alſo after <hi>Jupiter,</hi> but 'tis that of <hi>Gany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medes</hi> ſteep'd in Nectar and Ambroſia. Now I ſound the depth of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, neither am I quite deceiv'd by thoſe Rhetoricians of the Gods, the Poets. Now I perceive that they were not the Loves of <hi>Jupiter</hi> but our <hi>own</hi> which clothed the Deity in ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy forms.</p>
            <p>But becauſe ſlippery and wandring Love never reſts till 'tis arrived to the Pinnacle of perfection, or by a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing deluſion thinks ſo at leaſt, being always a Companion of the beſt and <note place="margin">Love is only of one.</note> greateſt, or what appears ſo, to this it muſt always adhere, in this always acquieſce, as the Heaven of its ſoul, the Center of its fire. The Lover will not I preſume be at leiſure to entertain the Charms (if there can be any) of a new felicity, neither will he find in his heart to Love an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, no nor himſelf. He will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver complain of the diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between his power and his deſires, and that he is wanting to him
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:106094:39"/>
whom he ſurfeits and wearies with exceſs of fondneſs. And after he has thus made over all his affection to one, and ſtill thinks he has not done enough, he muſt needs have as little Courteſie left for all others as a <hi>Monk</hi> or <hi>Stoick.</hi> Begon thou Monſter of <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racuſe</hi> who haſt invented a new Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny to thy other cruelties, a <hi>Pair-Royal</hi> in friendſhip. Who wouldeſt not kill a pair of friends, but divide them, and corrupt their fidelity by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terception of it, from a <hi>Tyrant</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into a <hi>Rival.</hi> But tell me Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ſuppoſe you were aſſumed a third Lover into the League of this pair, tell me which would you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in kindneſs? You muſt needs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe the other, now on the ſame ſcore jealous of your ſelf. But if you will diſtribute your kindneſs equally, ſuppoſe one of them brought to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, will you die for this, or live for the ſake of the other? You ſtand like a dubious needle between two Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones, by the neighborhood of two reſolutions detain'd from both. The diſtraction of your wiſh prompts you at once to live and die. Thus the <hi>Pendulous</hi> Lover about to adhere
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:106094:40"/>
to neither, and to both, is undone by this equality of affection. One ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acts tears from you, the other an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of laughter. The partiality of your officiouſneſs to one, makes you injurious to the other. So that your mind diſtracted ſeveral ways like <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> between the contrary draughts of Horſes, ſeems deſervedly to ſuffer the puniſhment of his perfidiouſneſs. Thus it happens as often as you undertake to be a <hi>Pluraliſt</hi> in affection, and at once to Love whom you can hardly ſee at the ſame time, unleſs you were ſquint-eyed or double-faced. Do but conſider the dominion and compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance which is in Love; Here the new <hi>Eteocles</hi> and <hi>Polynices</hi> muſt duly command and ſerve by turns, both of theſe are of a ſingular nature, and will not admit of two ſharers. If you fanſie Love to be a God, he Loves to reſide in one Heaven, if fire that alſo is confined to one Sphere, if death the Gods forbid a frequent expiration, or that we ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſouls to the boſome of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other more than once, ſince they grant us but once to <hi>live.</hi> Or if you call a Lover the Mirror, Coin or Seal
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106094:40"/>
of his dear object (all which receive both form and value from the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) know then that this looking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs can be inform'd but with one intire image at a time, that this Coin can be innobled with the face but of one King, that this Seal like that of a letter is cloſed faſt to all but one, and that all theſe are not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of a new impreſſion without the defacing of the former. But if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">Polygamy in the marriage of Souls is as bad as inceſt.</note> that friendſhip is nothing leſs than the <hi>Marriage</hi> of Souls, you ſhould think it an hanious Crime in theſe Maſculin Hymens to admit <hi>Polygamy,</hi> by ſuperinducing a new one to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marry the old, and to <hi>Cuckold</hi> ones friend.</p>
            <p>Does then that Paſſion which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhes <note place="margin">Yet it is ſo of one as not to be inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward all others.</note> humane Societies from the Herds of the field by too much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votedneſs bring men about again to the level of Beaſts, and to Stoical bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barity, the contempt of all? And muſt he who loves one intirely, hate all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind beſides? The gods forbid. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing certainly is more courteous than Love and Philoſophy, nothing more generous, nothing (except the gods) affords a greater Patronage to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106094:41"/>
the world. The very familiarity of friendſhip makes their minds eaſie and ſoft, and diſpoſes them to benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, juſt as a marriage does young Brides, who now put off their Coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <note place="margin">But ſo as a new bride leſs diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult and coy.</note> and uſe more freedom of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation towards all others. They com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate their Rays like the Sun to the whole world, though they gild <hi>Rhodes</hi> with a <hi>peculiar</hi> and <hi>diſtinguiſhing</hi> Luſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. You muſt know that one man is dedicated to another juſt like a book, ſent to one, but to be read by all, yet after the peruſal of that one. We owe much gratitude to thoſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did and generous Souls ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling the genius of Heaven, in that they favour not one only man but all mankind with a benign influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: Who as if they were the firſt Parents look upon all Nations as their own families, eſteem all as dear to them as their kindred, and as if they were born every where, or had an amplitude of mind equal, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurate to the whole Globe, ſtand affected to every Country as their Native one, and ſo deſervedly find it. But this we don't call friendſhip but a certain benevolence and <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:106094:41"/>
courteſie. Neither do we find <note place="margin">Polyphily is not friendſhip but bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence and a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring courteſie.</note> fault with this, or accept it with leſs Candor than they uſe even to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their enemies. But we would only curb the too wanton and Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affections of thoſe who pride them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the number of Salutations, and retinue of friends no leſs than in a guard of lackies, ambitious as much of the badges of Vertue as of State, and loving to <hi>ſweat</hi> in the throng of Clients. But this is the manner of proud Ladies who are not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtock'd <note place="margin">Polyphily without benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is not ſo much as courteſie, but ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of pride and laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> with chaſtity with a pretence of obligingneſs to inſnare others af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, openly to diſpence their kind Embraces, but ſtill as to one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſtudiouſly to compoſe a face, to level particular nods at <hi>him</hi> and <hi>him,</hi> to ſcatter up and down enticing glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to divide here and there flattering ſmiles: And laſtly, as it were to <hi>betroth</hi> their ſouls. And aſſoon as the prey is inveigled (as it frequently falls out) to withdraw the enchanting <hi>lure.</hi> O the moſt vile ſort of pride! To number the flocks of their Lovers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt of their feminine intereſts and improvements of Beauty.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:106094:42"/>
But ſince whoſoever is hot in the higheſt degree of true genuine fire, has not the will to Love leſs, nor the power to Love more: Neither is it enough that he diſregards others, unleſs he alſo contemn himſelf, and deny himſelf as well as others a ſhare in his own flames, freezing within his own Sphere, and remaining a cold <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamander</hi> in the midſt of the incir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cling flames. Since he is wholely remov'd from his own breaſt, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets himſelf, is wholely concern'd for his friend, and fears nothing on his own behalf, unleſs leſt he ſhould not act the part of a friend as he ought. Since he is wiſe for another, and blind as to his own intereſt, committing himſelf to the Fates, or to what is a greater ſafeguard, the care of his friend. (For he on the other hand is as much concern'd with fears and forecaſts in his behalf. He inſpirits him like an <hi>aſſiſting</hi> form, ſo that he reſembles the Heavens in being govern'd by an intelligence.) Since I ſay he thus renounces himſelf whoſoever inſerts himſelf into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and conſigns himſelf as one dead to Oblivion; and ſince (as it
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:106094:42"/>
ſhould be) the only dear thing to him is his friend, in whom he enjoys a more vital life after death, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout whom he ſportfully hovers like a pale Ghoſt about his body; <hi>The School-man of Amours has ſtated an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt meaſure rather of hatred than af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, the Love of one ſelf: And has done ill in propoſing us to our ſelves as patterns of Heroical Love.</hi> For of what ſmall account is every one with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? Where is that man who not capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated to anothers deſires, nor ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd with manners not his own, does live leſs to another than to himſelf? Neither is it to be imputed to our vices but to our Vertues, that we become Vaſſals to anothers pleaſure. Some Vertues are ſevere upon their owners, and are never diſſerviceable but to our ſelves, which yet to others bring in a great income. That modeſty which promotes its own diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and humbly diſlikes all purple but that of a bluſhing face, <hi>ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> of contempt, yet transfers the Encomiums due to it ſelf upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a ſteel'd boldneſs. That ambition which toiles on anothers ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count is graced with the title of fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106094:43"/>
and Candour. That armour which is worn on the breaſt does but only forge a man into a ſhield <hi>Errant</hi> for the defence of others, though with the expence of his own ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. No man dy's for the mere prevention of his own death, but that he may intercept the fatal ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row from his Parents, Children, or ſome others. What did I ſay, no man dies? No man lives on his own account. But if bare nature and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Vertue without friendſhip can produce ſuch a combination or rather <hi>ſelf-dedication,</hi> that every one ſhould count himſelf the leaſt part of himſelf, let it be a ſhame that friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (which adds to Vertues new ſtrength, accompliſhment and huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) ſhould preſcribe any other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <note place="margin">The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolence ſhould be to know none.</note> to benevolence beſides this one, to know none at all, or circumſcribe any other limits than thoſe which are mark'd out by the deſires of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. Let him not Love at all (and I am ſure I cannot imprecate a heavier Curſe) who tempers his affection and is not rather ruled by it, who warily Loves to ſuch a ſet degree as if ready to hate, or who deals out his
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:106094:43"/>
affection in proportions, giving and receiving favours with a pair of ſcales. He may perhaps <hi>return</hi> Love but not Love <hi>directly,</hi> who anſwers his Lover juſt as he pledges his Companion, preciſely <hi>ſo much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I ſtand amuſed with a long veneration, like a ſweetly confuſed <hi>Inamorato</hi> who has waſted all his eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight upon a Divine form, and is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain even after the greateſt <hi>Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm</hi> of interview, which part of the Soveraign Beauty firſt deſerves his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, and is arrived only thus far, to admire his own aſtoniſhment, and to pay equal adoration to all the excellencies, as if every one were ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, and variouſly to aſſent to the praiſes of parties differently affected. I hear <hi>Dionyſius</hi> defining <hi>Love to be a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions of Love. It is a Circle returning from good through good to good. <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Circle returning from good through good to good.</hi> And I confeſs 'tis comprehended in this ingenious Emblem. Hence I look upon a Ring not only as a <hi>pledge</hi> but an <hi>Hieroglyphick</hi> of Love. <hi>Cupid</hi> repreſents to me this Circle while he is bending his bow, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſemicircle of his own body. This Circle is decypher'd to me by the continual heat of Lovers,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:106094:44"/>
which with the blood is carried round (according to the modern Tenet of Phyſicians) in a Circular motion. 'Tis like the Elementary fire where the immortal flame feeds it ſelf, and is its own fuel; whoever loves that which he hath lov'd retreats by a ſpherical motion in his own track: and he that loves only that he may Love, the ſame returns upon himſelf, cloſes up himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> tells me (and I eaſily <note place="margin">The whole Myſtery of Love con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to that from whence we were. <hi>Ariſtopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi>
               </note> believe him) that <hi>the whole myſtery of Love conſiſts in being reduced to that from whence we were.</hi> For I ſee all things by a natural motion retire into their principles. And perhaps thoſe Magnetick Charms which they fanſie to be lodg'd in the whole earth, are found by Philoſphers, Mariners and ſhips to be only in the Native Country. The Law of nature obliges us to beſtow our lives upon thoſe from whom we receiv'd them, and by a certain ſeries of piety and Scale of alliance, to adore thoſe three names dearer than our lives, our <hi>Country, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents'</hi> and <hi>God.</hi> I know not whether I may call man (like <hi>Oedipus)</hi> a blind and inceſtuous Lover, or rather pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:106094:44"/>
and pious, who is always ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor'd with ſomething of his original, and is as cordially affected toward it as to his Parent. Neither is he much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, who takes that for his Parent whence he dates the rudiments of a new life, and by a kind of revival renews his Nativity at the expence of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Love. Thus to reſign up our ſouls is to retrieve and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make them. But you O <hi>Thales,</hi> by leaping into the water, and you <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedocles</hi> into the fire, the one by chance and the other out of deſign, made too much haſt to reſolve not only <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> but the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into their principles, and to plunge the vital particles of your ſouls into their Elements. But yet ſo the errors of this Philoſophy excuſe thoſe of the affections, and ſince our hungry Souls as well as bodies are nouriſh'd with thoſe things whereof they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt; you'd ſwear the Drunkard had a liquid Soul, and the Tyrant a bloody one infuſed into them, you'd ſwear the fordid miſers were juſt inlivened out of the mud, and that the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ical and barbarous were hewn out of a Cragged Rock, and ſo ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:106094:45"/>
the Statues of men. But if we fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie with <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> in <hi>Plato</hi> that from <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plato's Conviv.</hi>
               </note> the common ſeminary of ſouls, or from the joynt Society of a man here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore double-body'd, the familiar and <hi>Colleague-Souls</hi> were ſent into the world, methinks this they render probable, while like the parts of a divided inſect, they ſeek out for th' o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther half, or when they run into em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces at firſt ſight, as perſons mindful of their former intimacy. So that the Platonick man is now all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver memory, whoſe <hi>Love</hi> as well as <hi>Philoſophy</hi> is nothing elſe but <hi>Remini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea rather whoſe Love is the very <note place="margin">The firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy is the deſire of Eternity. <hi>Diotima.</hi>
               </note> exerciſe of Philoſophy (for I willingly and deſervedly aſcribe both to you <hi>Diotima)</hi> that is, to elevate our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-born Souls together with their bodies to a perpetual intuition of Heaven (juſt as the bird of the Sun is fed only with his Raies) and to vegetate them with a deſire of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. This is that Myſterious ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour which makes us Mortals always emulous of Divine perfection out of Love with the meanneſs of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and for a remedy haſtens to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:106094:45"/>
ſtrip the man of the part which is frail. Hence as if we had a Legion of eyes, we take a proſpect (which is more than the Sun himſelf can do) of both ends of the earth at once. Hence <hi>Amphitryo</hi> could at once diſcharge the affairs of his Houſe and of the Camp, and though remote accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny his Wife, and that not (as the Poets will have it) in the fiction of diſguiſe. Hence circumſcribed with no bounds either of time or ſpace, we live another life after the firſt, either in our friends the Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians of our now alienated ſouls, or in our Children the Heirs of our tranſmitted life, both lending and borrowing breath.</p>
            <p>While I muſe on theſe thoughts, <note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of enjoying Beauty. <hi>Plato.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Plato</hi> offers me a nearer experiment: And I preſently turn'd Platonick, ſwear that this <hi>Cupid</hi> (though never ſo blind, and content only with thought where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he perſues Divine Objects, and yet born from the ſight) <hi>is nothing but a deſire of enjoying and forming Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in ſomething Beautiful.</hi> The truth is we are willing to enjoy, not being able always to content our ſelves with the barren delight of Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:106094:46"/>
and Courtſhip, that from the conflux of aſſociated ſplendor, as from the Conjunction of Stars, the Glory and influence may encreaſe, and our Star improve into a Conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. And as Pictures, ſo faces of too Majeſtick Beauty whoſe blandiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are above our fortune and hopes, affect the ſpectators with ſome pleaſure, no deſire. And that por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Beauty which recreates the ſight with the ſweetneſs of Symmetry and Complexion <hi>only,</hi> will find more ſpectators than lovers, as ſetting forth the prettineſs and graces of a delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome proſpect, ſuch as are better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in painted than living faces. Nothing that's barren and dead excites vital affections, nothing that's inanimate influences the Soul. Neither is there greater pleaſure in <note place="margin">And of forming it in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Beautiful.</note> enjoying than in forming of Beauty. There's a natural energy which pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges the mind as well as face with the art of imaging it ſelf, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it fixes its aſpect. Hence 'tis that all Beauty delights in a Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſs, and rather than want a ſpectator applies it ſelf to its own image looking back on it ſelf. I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:106094:46"/>
to you <hi>Socrates</hi> the Maſter both of Love and Morality, whoſe employment was the ſame when a Philoſopher, and when heretofore a Statuary. You ſtill continue your old trade of carving and polliſhing men, but you ſeek out more excellent materials whereby to dignifie your Mechaniſm. And for this reaſon you ſtock your School like a <hi>Seraglio</hi> with ſuch handſome pupils as <hi>Phaedrus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Nothing is lov'd but under the notion of Beatiful.</note> and <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> who might eaſily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibe your ſoul, and return you your image with advantage, as being more clear than a Looking-glaſs, more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der than wax. Whatſoever that is which like the Stars with its heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly light tranſcends the envy of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, invites a Religious awe and with a ſpecious lure intices Souls to it ſelf, does indeed ſo wholely poſſeſs them as not to ſuffer them to turn aſide to another object. Nothing can dazle and inflame our minds but what is preſented to us under the tincture of theſe Raies, but what moves and ſtrikes upon the ſenſes. Our very vices impoſe upon us under the amiable mask of Vertues. And as often as we are pleas'd to err with nature,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:106094:47"/>
and with a <hi>Croſs grain'd</hi> Love to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in ſuch Children which their Parents behold with horror, as often as we ſeek among herds and Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters for ſomething to be adopted into humane ſociety as well as into a Conſtellation, we have this pleaſant priviledge to boaſt of, that we need not fear a rival, and to pretend an <hi>incongruous</hi> diverſion in the jarrings of nature, and laſtly to be able to ſhew ſomething to the beholders more ugly than our ſelves. Unleſs <note place="margin">Becauſe nothing is deform'd in Nature.</note> ſome will maintain that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing deform'd in nature, ſince thoſe Creatures which the Author of them has doom'd to obſcurity as the <hi>ſhame</hi> of the Creation, leſt they ſhould defile the light, have a decency from their very horror, and ſet off the face of the univerſe like Moles and ſhades. For we ought not preſently to conclude that which is leſs grateful to the ſight to be down-right ugly, but a rare and unuſual ſpectacle, and ſuch as the nice and curious uſe to procure at any Coſt. What may not there be Sacred where owls and the moſt vile Creatures, have been deified, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor'd by men? Where ſince there is
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106094:47"/>
no deformity, neither is there any ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, <note place="margin">There is nothing alſo of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred or Antipathy in things.</note> nor the name of <hi>Antipathy</hi> uſed but among the Sects of Philoſophers? why do you tell me among your lectures of ſobriety how much the Colewort de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines the Vine? Even as much as the abſtemious patient upon the advice of a Phyſician, not becauſe he loaths the wine, or for the ſake of temperance, but merely to conſult his health. So the Wolf preys upon the Lamb, and the fire upon the water, not out of any ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terd, but for ſelf-preſervation. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they avenge injuries, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by the moſt cloſe embrace to convert another into themſelves. So neither does one man abhor the perſon of another, but only his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity as a vice, and ſo is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for <hi>himſelf.</hi> Neither do we envy other men their endowments for any ſpite we have at <hi>them,</hi> but are only too ſollicitous for <hi>our ſelves,</hi> either becauſe we think anothers cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit a diminution of our own, or elſe becauſe willing to become <hi>cheaply</hi> good, we would adopt the Vertues of others to our ſelves with the ſole labour of a wiſh. If there be any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention in nature, ſure 'tis a loving one,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:106094:48"/>
ſuch as conſtitutes and increaſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths, a <hi>Social</hi> robbery, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting our welfare by alternate loſſes, neither are theſe to be call'd ſpoils, but gifts indulg'd by courſe. Ah cruel Love, if theſe Wars were managed by your darts, if <hi>Helen</hi> muſt be ſtill obtain'd through Rapin and Slaughter, and <hi>Venus</hi> muſt belong only to <hi>Mars!</hi> And yet 'tis worth the while to die that we may indear her to us. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I wonder ſince an ambitious vying for Beauty bred a quarrel among Goddeſſes, if poor <hi>Paris</hi> and the reſt of Mortals with rival ambition ſhould put in for the fair prize. From the time that Love the parent of the world wrought out a Symphony from the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of things, and wedded together <hi>Vulcan</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> in a mutual Embrace, that is, flames and waters, and cemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">Love the Artificer of things, and their Beauty was like other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers the firſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of its own work.</note> the moſt diſagreeing things in a ſort of <hi>checquer-work.</hi> From the time I ſay that he hung out this great frame of the Univerſe, like a rich Map adorn'd with Beauty and order, he ſtood himſelf like other Artificers the firſt Judge and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirer of his own work, &amp; made the firſt experiment of thoſe Charms of Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which he himſelf imparted. This is
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:106094:48"/>
(if you would know) that order of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from which things derive not ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and infirmity, but at once Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament and Compactneſs. I take Beauty to be nothing elſe but the Conſummation, Quinteſſence and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity of every thing. I think that <note place="margin">That is Beautiful which is all that it ſhould be. Beauty is not ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs but the vigour and ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing The ſame innate vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour gives decency, ſtrength and Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Beautiful and ſplendid which is all that which it ſhould be. Obſerve how the ſame innate vigour gives ſtrength and Beauty to the Arm, how jewels throughly imbued with it ſend forth ſoft Raies among their rigid ſparklings! How the lively moiſture at the root makes fertil, and adorns with the Verdure of an Emerald! Thus we find all by experience and yet ceaſe not from wonder, that a mind compoſed within ſmooths out the forehead, an ingenuous Texture of thoughts recommends the face be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the greateſt Artifice of dreſs, and that a refined mind ſerenes more than the blood. The Soul ſhines through her Native Veil as a Ladie's face through that of Silk, or as the <note place="margin">Beauty is a certain ſublimate of the body, the Flower of internal Vertue. An eflux of the ſoul. All Beauty conſiſts of Proportion, of the knowledge of the ſoul and the manners of the body.</note>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:106094:49"/>
obſcurer Sun diſpenſes his Raies here and there and <hi>Strains</hi> day-light through a cloud. I am apt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Divine gueſt does chooſe out a fit habitation for it ſelf, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to its proportion like Snails, forms a houſe contemporary and equal to its owner. So graphically does the body expreſs the lineaments of the ſoul, that no Garment ſeems more diſtinctly to decypher thoſe of the body. This, this is that brightneſs of the unſullied ſoul which illuſtrates every feature, and moulds the limbs into legible Characters, that by the likeneſs of ſouls others may be allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, till the Original form being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd and the Deity within diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd, the earthy mould be diſregard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For alas what an inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing is that Beauty of a face which entertains our eyes with the daily ſpring of freſh graces, which we ſhew one to another in a rapture, and although poſſeſs'd with a <hi>Rival</hi> concern, yet call in <hi>Auxiliary</hi> votaries to ſhare in our admiration? We are taken only with a ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, a Colour, a reflexion of light, yea a moſt empty ſhadow, which if we
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106094:49"/>
gaze long upon, it wears away and diſappears before our eyes. And what a poor little thing is that frame and Structure of Limbs delineated as with a Rule and Compaſs? If that be all, <note place="margin">Beauty is conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonancy and ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion and lines or frame of moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> Statues may boaſt of a neater out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide than man, and the houſe of a more elegant model than the inhabitant. What an inconſiderable thing is that motion which lends ſuch a graceful mean to bodies imitable by no Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? Suppoſe it more ſoft and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form than the <hi>Downy</hi> glidings of the Celeſtial Orbs or of time, Careleſs, looſe and unaffected, it has this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apology for its meanneſs, that while it pleaſes, leſt it ſhould alſo prove tedious, it paſſes away, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct even while it begins. But all this while I ſeem too partial to the errors of Lovers, and the Encomiums of Beauty, by ſuppoſing all that which <note place="margin">All the grace of the body is either imaginary or the paint of opinion.</note> is thought handſome in bodies to be the ſhadows and imitations of a real decency, and not rather the dreams of imagination, and the paint of our own opinion. For 'tis not that which we behold, but what we imagin to our ſelves, that we are in Love with. Tell me if you can whence it comes
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:106094:50"/>
to paſs that the ſame face is of ſo mutable a Beauty, as to cauſe an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation in others when they meet it, which to you tranſcends the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Stars? Whence is it that ſome are mightily inamour'd with the ſoft and hypocritical reſemblance of the other ſex, and others again are more taken with the ſomewhat more than maſculin horror of an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poliſh'd</hi> countenance? Whence is it that to ſome what is ſo little as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to eſcape the ſight is the more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, under the notion of delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and prettineſs; and to others again that which is ample and <hi>fills</hi> the eyes, ſeems the only comely and Majeſtick object? Why, the changeable co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of a pretty face like Pigeons necks borrows an imaginary Beauty which it has not, from various aſpects, and diverſity of poſtures.</p>
            <p>I'll deliver my thoughts with free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: What ever that appearance is which feeds the eyes, 'tis either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aginary and of ſuch a nature that we muſt needs loſe it when awaken'd <note place="margin">Or if real, 'tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to detain the ſoul.</note> out of our ſweet dream; or if real, 'tis unworthy to terminate our ſouls, and ſhould only provoke, inform and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106094:50"/>
ſend them farther. How can that ſtrike ſo gratefully on the mind, which the eye only enjoys and knows not how to communicate? For the contagion of no Beauty except that of the mind, is ſo great as to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe it ſelf on the beholder as on Water or a looking-glaſs. It muſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way reſemble God and our own ſouls, that is be incorporeal, whatſoever <note place="margin">It muſt be of kin to God and our own Souls that is incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real, what ever lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in the mind. Even that Beauty of the body is imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial.</note> does but ſojourn in our minds, much leſs is adopted by the affections. Although even that very air of the body of how little force ſoever, be alſo ſomething immaterial, and like the ſoul rules at large, <hi>all in all, and all in every part.</hi> 'Tis eaſily to be ſeen, there is ſome efflux, Ray and I know not what vigor either of the ſoul or of an Idea, which running through all the actions diffuſes it ſelf through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ever member, and aſſimulating all things to it ſelf, collects the <hi>Syſteme</hi> of graces into the face, where they ſettle as in their center.</p>
            <p>Here the Boy <hi>Cupid</hi> keeps his Court <note place="margin">But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſhadow of Beauty breeds on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Love.</note> enthroned in the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of Beauty, here he plays with the beholders, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rles his darts from the wanton flaſhes of eyes, and hurles living flames. Here
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106094:51"/>
indeed Love plaies in his minority, but when grown to maturity he chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es both his Camp and Artillery, firſt ſeating himſelf in the middle region be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the mind and the body, the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect,</hi> he ſports innocently in the confines of both. But by and by he advances up to the Soul and enjoys a pure and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphick</hi> flame, or deſcends to the body and like a <hi>Meteor</hi> deceives with a groſs and fallacious blaze. And to uſe no more undervaluing invectives, this one thing abundantly confirms the infelicity of this Paſſion, that it always has more influence on the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent than the preſent, and that the ſight or Embrace of a body does al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways drive us either to loathing or madneſs. What God is this which <note place="margin">The error of this Paſſion is puniſh'd with ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſdain.</note> Chaſtiſes the madneſs of erring <hi>Cupid</hi> with his own deſires? Who is't com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels him ſtill to languiſh for what he enjoys moſt of all, and ſo Paſſionately to refuſe what juſt now he more paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately long'd for? He proteſts theſe were not the joys he ſought for, but that while he ſtood unreſolv'd what he ſhould deſire, and follow'd the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct rather of his eyes than judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he lighted upon them by a blind
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:106094:51"/>
and unthinking tendency. But becauſe theſe are the ſhadows of that which the mind hankers after, ſhe wings away preſently to them like a bird deceiv'd with painted Grapes, but with them as with <hi>phantaſtick</hi> food ſhe's rather <note place="margin">In the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the ſhadow of divine Beauty, in the ſoul the likenſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d, in both a deity un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Type.</note> tormented than fed. I muſt nevertheleſs acknowledge (ſince they who ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rangue moſt ſharply againſt it, feel the influence more vehemently than they deny it) that theſe ſhadows of Beauty will beget alſo ſhadows of Love. And as in the Soul we adore the ſimilitude of God, ſo do we a certain ſhadow of him in the body, in both we worſhip a Deity under a Type, and by an ignorant devotion become Courters of Divinity. For there's <note place="margin">Beauty whether a Ray o God, or a reflexion of an Idea, or an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flux of the ſoul, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſomething divine; becauſe 'tis the property of man to love Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> the ſame proportion between the mind and God, as between the eye and the Sun; from whoſe light it gains thus much, that it ſees, and that it neither delights nor is able to ſee any thing elſe without the ſight of him, and yet can't endure to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the fulneſs of his luſtre, and therefore loves to receive his Raies at ſecond hand, to view the Image of his corrected ſplendor, and to refreſh it ſelf with feeble delights and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106094:52"/>
ſhadows. Whatever that is (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Ray of God, or a reflection of an Idea, or an efflux of the Soul) which under the ſhew of Beauty cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivates the eyes and mind, muſt be ſomething Divine, ſince 'tis the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of man alone to contemplate and be affected with Beauty.</p>
            <p>Pardon me if I alſo raviſh'd with the Love of Beauty, am carried beyond all bounds, and leave even my ſelf behind through the extravagance of tranſport. I am willing to abide here, where I find Love inthroned in the moſt Beautiful part of the world, <hi>in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I can't forbear venting my anger on thoſe mortifi'd and <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical,</hi> Ghoſts (whoſe Sage Morals li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe them to diſlike every thing) who condemn all the Erratas of humanity as the intemperance of ſolid benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, who inveigh againſt this god <hi>Cupid,</hi> as the ringleader to all luxury and voluptuouſneſs, and the <hi>Ingineer</hi> of all Tragick intreagues and vallainies, whom we find our <hi>Proxy</hi> to gain us immortality, and the Author of a Divine nature. This is the reward of all <note place="margin">Simple and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a Love.</note> ſimple and barren Love, which it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:106094:52"/>
from its own luxurious boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (for where there is no return of gratitude, Love has the ſame reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue with liberality) it has repay'd it ſelf. 'Tis an abundant reward to have well deſerv'd. And yet there's a <note place="margin">Love and Love for Love are Twins born and growing up toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> greater reward than all this ſought after by Love, to be paid in kind, when ſouls growing warm together intermingle flames and light awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened by mutual alliſion (as one piece of Iron whets another) and cheriſh their ardours by a reciprocal propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. They live to one another mutually by an exchange of ſpirits, and in the bottom of their hearts juſt as in that of tranſparent water, their faces anſwer each other by repercuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Certainly nothing is more ſweet than to Love <hi>or</hi> to be lov'd, except this, to Love <hi>and</hi> to be lov'd.</p>
            <p>For when our Love is unhappily miſplaced, and ſuch creatures are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troth'd to our Embraces which either by a certain neceſſity of Nature, or by their own fault are ingrateful: When with nuptial ſolemnity <hi>Xerxes</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces <hi>Plato, Polydorus</hi> a Statue and <hi>Lesbia</hi> a Sparrow not more wiſhing for, than undergoing a Metamorpho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:106094:53"/>
and find the Poetical fables veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd in themſelves being all over anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Deity of Love, and by the <hi>plaſtick</hi> power and <hi>aſſimulating</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity of affection converted into trees, ſtones and Birds, 'tis not the leaſt of all felicity (when there is no other way of Society but that the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon perſonate a Companion to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) to feign dialogues, anſwers and delights proper to ones ſelf, and ſo to model our happineſs to our own, not anothers liking. Methinks it pleaſes me to ſee the not altogether fruitleſs affection return upon its Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, where that is the refuge of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light which in Amours is eſteem'd the chiefeſt, to Love again our own Love, and like the Sun enjoy our own heat by reflexion at leaſt.</p>
            <p>Neither does leſs pleaſure, but more honour attend that other lot, to be belov'd. Whence men more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally court others affections than they impart their own. For this is like gods to extend their Dominions in mens hearts without the Pageantry of a Sceptre. This diſplaies the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our fortunes and Vertues, and makes us oftener receive
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106094:53"/>
the officious ſervices of others, than perform any our ſelves. Thus the Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies of your excellencies become con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous according to the number of Captive Clients which follow your triumph.</p>
            <p>But when on both ſides there is an equal contention of officiouſneſs, when there is a <hi>Duel</hi> of Courteſie not with complemental Oſtentation, but with the higheſt ſhame of yielding and fear <note place="margin">Mutual Love is a parity of reciprocal benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi>
               </note> of leſs obliging, then ariſes that pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of reciprocal benevolence which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> honours with that well known name though of rare inſtance, <hi>friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Venus</hi> felt theſe reciprocal tides at her birth, and ſo ſtill continues a <hi>flux</hi> and <hi>reflux</hi> of affection. That equality which that <hi>Leveller</hi> juſtice has been a long time to no purpoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring with her Sword and ballance, Love with eaſe introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into the world, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways finds equals or makes them ſo. Sometimes the diſtances of fortune and merit, cut off the bands of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip oftner than thoſe of place. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> muſt deſcend to the earth and put off the Raies of his Divinity, if he be minded to enjoy the Embraces
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:106094:54"/>
of Mortals. And ſo he did; nay for fear leſt he ſhould not be familiar and deſpicable enough, he degraded himſelf below a man into a <hi>Brute</hi> Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſo procured himſelf eaſie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſooner by contemtibleneſs than majeſtick horrour. <hi>If you will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced</hi> Sextus, <hi>I ſh'ant Love you.</hi> The ſtory of <hi>Semele</hi> ſufficiently informs what a great and <hi>proud</hi> puniſhment 'tis to <hi>endure</hi> the Society of a God. The Moral's good. An officious cringing <note place="margin">Officiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons is flattery and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion, not Love and fidelity.</note> to great perſonages ſweet only to the unexperienced, comes nearer to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery than benevolence, and is always ſuſpected as an inſinuating Art of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaking more than we offer. 'Twas your ambition which brought you hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not your ſincerity, ſo that you deſerve a place among my ſervants, not among my friends. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are at an equal pitch, when I diſappoint you of your hoped for dignity, as you would have brought me down from mine. Yet ſometimes <note place="margin">'Tis ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude not friendſhip.</note> we find humble Superiors <hi>ambitious</hi> of condeſcenſion, chooſing a reflection upon their <hi>Scutcheon,</hi> before a diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their <hi>Courteſie. Alexander</hi> acts no longer the Emperours part, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:106094:54"/>
loſes thoſe titles in Love which he had won in Conqueſt. But he loſes them with greater glory to <hi>Hepheſtion,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that <hi>Hepheſtion</hi> might be King, ſo that himſelf might be a part of his Kingdom. He makes over all thoſe honourable courtſhips which he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from others to <hi>Hepheſtion,</hi> while he ſerves his <hi>Hepheſtion</hi> he ſeems to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large his territories, and to enjoy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other world. We all acknowledge Love to be a ſweet and reſtleſs deſire of pleaſing them, who (either by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident or their own Vertues, or laſtly our own miſtake) have any way grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd us. It matters not much as in life ſo in friendſhip what e'r is the Origin of the heat. It inlivens the heart with a never the leſs durable and daily moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The importunate votary reſolving to tire or overcome you, or indear <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Barclay's Icon Anim.</hi>
               </note> and pleaſe you, heaps one good turn upon an other, and when there is no more room for his officiouſneſs, he ſerves with empty endeavours, and looking ſtill like one doing good, obliges by his very <hi>Well meaning</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance. He cautiouſly fathoms the inclinations of his friend by heedful
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:106094:55"/>
experiments, and for the very ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous fear of diſpleaſing deſerves to pleaſe. He thinks it of great uſe ſometimes to have diſpleas'd, that ſo he may either hate or correct his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour. For to be as much like him as is poſſible is all one he thinks with being good and happy. Wherefore he feels his pulſe more <hi>ſcrupulouſly</hi> than a Phyſician, examines the moſt inward motions of his breaſt, ſerves him upon ſtrong preſumptions, and executes his wiſhes ſcarce yet known to himſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they diſcompoſe him with the firſt <hi>qualms</hi> of a <hi>breeding</hi> deſire. Neither will he ever ſatisfie himſelf though he has the other abundantly, that it may appear he indulges his officious inſtinct not with a deſign of inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but for the bare pleaſure of ſerving, as if by the <hi>predeſtination</hi> of nature he were <hi>mark'd out</hi> for a ſlave to this one perſon.</p>
            <p>You ſhall know (ſince you are ſo inquiſitive) that there is a pedigree and origin of Love as well as life. There is an order and mutual reſpect between ſome either inſtituted by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Simplicius</hi> upon <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tus.</hi>
               </note> or voluntarily undertaken; and this again is either among perſons of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:106094:55"/>
like or unlike diſpoſitions, which occaſions the union of ſome, and the diſſociation of others. But as for that ty of blood, 'tis a mere Contingent thing; ſuch as argues no merit of bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence, which becauſe obtruded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our unconſenting breaſts, we did not admit, but unknowingly ſuſtain. And now it brings as much of burthen with it as of neceſſity, and what is worſe, this <hi>Lottery</hi> of birth, impoſes upon as a neceſſity of honouring even the moſt wicked and vile perſons, and what's more againſt the hair yet, it exacts every where an equal and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon rate of affection, according to the cuſtom of Countrys, ſuch as muſt not be diminiſhed, and yet can't well be improv'd higher. Pardon me ye Ghoſts <note place="margin">The name of friend more Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred than that of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</note> of my kindred, if I adore the name of <hi>Friend,</hi> as far more Sacred than that of <hi>Parent.</hi> We indeed owe all that to Love, which by the hereditary er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of an eaſie piety we aſcribe to our Parents. For it happens from their own mutual Love not from any kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to us (whom they knew not they ſhould produce but from the Oracle) that we enjoy the benefit of this light. And we with as little natural kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106094:56"/>
for them rejoice to ſee the light, not our parents, and being as igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of them as they were before of us, are apt to beſtow our <hi>unprejudic'd</hi> Embraces on any elſe (as if they were our Parents, or might as well have been) with a fond innocency. So much Philoſophy we may learn from that little age, that we are not ſo much the off-ſpring of a man as of mankind, and born to all in common, and that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould ſhare in our <hi>filial</hi> grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. Neither are domeſtick friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips kindled and cheriſh'd by near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of blood, but converſation and the ſweet Society in calamities and errors, together with Congratulations ariſing from common miſeries. I am much <note place="margin">The union of will as far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds that of blood, as reaſon does na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> miſtaken if Lovers be not nearer of kin to one another, and engaged in ſo much the ſtraiter bond, by how much reaſon exceeds nature, and the force of my own choice is more prevalent than that of Conſanguinity. For 'tis the ſweetneſs of conforming to ones own Laws, which makes every man ſo conſtantly <hi>Loyal</hi> to himſelf. But when nature and choice ſhall both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire, with how prone and eaſie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct does that affection move the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106094:56"/>
mind, which flows from nature and will link'd together in a <hi>ſilent</hi> conſent! If it be our lot to be born and educated to the Love of any perſon (nature and ſtudious care contributing to faſhion us after his pattern) if the Stars of any mingled their lights before, in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable and friendly conjunctions, if the ſpecies of any be congenial and innate to us from our Nativity (for nature does ſometimes either for knowledge or defence like breeding mothers imprint ſome marks on the members) how greedily do we imbibe their aſpects as familiar to us from the Cradle, and more certainly known than by a long converſation! How do we redemand this image as a piece ſnatch'd from our own Souls! How do we ſwallow down the breath and voice of this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon like vital air! How do we run together with an indeliberate propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, without the Ceremony of kind ſalutations, like Lovers after abſence or divorce, renewing their Careſſes! Thus theſe ſouls involv'd all over in a <hi>Voluntary</hi> Slavery, engage in a mutual league, not tarrying who ſhall give the firſt Love-ſtroke. Juſt like thoſe who ſwear to, and ſign bonds without
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:106094:57"/>
ever reading them, and yet can never diſſolve the Sacred ty, nor cancel their <hi>ſolemn,</hi> though <hi>inconſiderate</hi> engagement. 'Tis anothers conſent and not their own which ratifi'd theſe engagements, ſo that they have made over the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of conſenting, nay the whole right of themſelves to the power and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of another.</p>
            <p>But O <hi>Cupid</hi> the leaſt of gods, and greateſt of Deities, I ſhould think it leſs than your deſerts (if yet there <note place="margin">Love is a God.</note> could be any thing greater) that you are Deifi'd by thoſe bold Philoſophers the Poets. You have this proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a god, to be unknown and to receive homage from men. You have this alſo of a god to govern men with a ſilent influence, that they may yield to your motions though not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by them, or elſe to draw them by compulſion. To the beck of whoſe Majeſty all contrary Paſſions pay Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance and attendance. As often as you are diſpoſed to divert your ſelf, the moſt high flown Pride ſtrikes Sail, the moſt daring courage trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles at the lucid Darts of an Eye; Covetouſneſs it ſelf turns Prodigal in a Voluntary Oblation of rich pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:106094:57"/>
and the ſuddainly Eloquent illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate Heir now no longer buys Poems with their Poets, but himſelf becomes <hi>inſpired</hi> and <hi>compoſes.</hi> And to paſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with religious ſilence your other Divine attributes, that you are a Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, Eternal, immenſe, and that you engroſs all that Office of Providence, to preſide over, and to preſerve, this one thing confirms in me the belief of your Divinity, that your only Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtrikes an awe into the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane. They ſo manage their Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as if they were performing ſome Religious Rite. They look paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, view their habit curiouſly, and compoſe themſelves to all the ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of reverence. And to what end all this? That they may addreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their Miſtreſs as to an Altar. Nay more, that they may be decent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when abſent. For whom we love we fanſie always preſent, the Judge of our actions, the ſupplier of vertuous and ingenious thoughts, the proſperer of all our Heroick under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings. Whom the Sailer ſupplicates for a calm, the Travailer for a ſafe return, the Souldier for Victory and booty, out of which he may make her
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:106094:58"/>
a preſent. Well, henceforth let it be permitted to Lovers to Complement one another with Metaphors fetch'd from Heaven, to Court in the Sacred <hi>Dialect</hi> of Religion.</p>
            <p>Neither do I think any one can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy at the Divinity of ſo mild a god, whoſe anger may be appeas'd without ſlaughter, who does not like other gods require beaſts, but only chearful Votaries for Sacrifice, and that he may not want Temples, erects flaming Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars in humane breaſts. Nay the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle god himſelf being converted into <note place="margin">It is fire.</note> fire, by a continual ſupply of flames takes care for his worſhip. 'Tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſo; as often as I ſee the penſive Inamorato venting his Paſſion in deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetch'd ſighs, he minds me of the fire which is immured in a Cloud redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling murmurs and thunders, and at laſt expiring in a fume. As often as I ſee him bedew'd with the <hi>ſweat</hi> of tears, and boiling over with groans, I call to mind the flames of <hi>Aetna</hi> and <hi>Veſuvius</hi> breaking out among the flames of Snow and Aſhes; or methinks I ſee the great <hi>Chaſms</hi> in the mid-ſea occaſion'd by the eruption of fire. As often as the ſhort-liv'd fire of a
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:106094:58"/>
counterfeit paſſion diſplays it ſelf in imaginary and <hi>Scenical</hi> flames, I then conſider in man fictitious blazes, fires reſembling thoſe of the Celeſtial Lamps, <hi>Meteors</hi> of affection. Again, Love in this reſpect reſembles fire, in that it ſerves only to the benefit of men, and the worſhip of the gods. Again, in that it heats and inlightens our fancies, inſomuch that <hi>Apollo</hi> as well as <hi>Bacchus</hi> owes his riſe to the flames of Love. Again, in that it rages againſt the <hi>Bars</hi> of oppoſition, gathers new ſtrength from allaies and impediments, and is fomented by inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and provocations as fire by the aſperſions of Water. Then as to the properties of the Ethereal fire it burns and refreſhes, is immortal without fuel, ſelf ſufficient, (for Love is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with it ſelf being its own reward) it is inviolable, not to be polluted by the Contagion of filthineſs, expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and purging the Crimes, which it cannot admit, equalling the Virgin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excellency of the Veſtal flames. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it has this one quality more of the Celeſtial fire, that for the ſecurity of the Univerſe it has obtain'd a ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of Station, that 'tis ſeated in the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:106094:59"/>
top of all, guarding and encloſing the inferiour Paſſions. In this one thing the parallel halts, that it extends its vital influence beyond its Sphere to the production and Conſervation of Animals. Thus is Love parallel'd with the two pureſt and moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things either above or under the Celeſtial Arch, <hi>God</hi> and <hi>fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But among all the Miracles of My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious Love this is the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding, <note place="margin">Occult Love like a ſubterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous fire burns, but gives no light out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</note> that often times in the interior parts of men as well as of the earth there glows a <hi>Subteraneous</hi> fire, which ſpreads its Contagious <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> without the leaſt outward <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptom</hi> of a blaze. So that when we feel it burn and yet can't give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count how it came to be kindled (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs any of us are of opinion that the flame was congenial to the breaſt, and upon the conviction of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment grant the ſoul to be fire) we deny it burns at all. So loth are we to own our ignorance by admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at the unaccountable harmony of ſouls equal to that of the Spheres; when every one has contrary motions of its own, and yet partakes of the ſame, as if govern'd by a certain
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:106094:59"/>
common Intelligence. 'Tis our daily wonder whence the ſtrings of hearts as well as thoſe of Lutes, mutually ſympathize with ſuch conſent, that the trepidations of the one are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded with the correſpondent Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor of the other. We ſtand amazed at the ſurpriſing ſymphony, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known even to the Muſician, and ſwear theſe ſtrings were heretofore <note place="margin">Motion is conſent as in bodies ſo in Souls.</note> taken out of or now skrew'd to a uniſon in the ſame entrails. Wee'l grant the Phyſicians their Paradox, that <hi>motion is only a certain conſent in bodies</hi> (a no ſmall advantage to their art) being well aſſured it holds true in ſouls.</p>
            <p>Neither let us any longer doubt to <note place="margin">Hence Love is a Magician.</note> affirm with <hi>Plato</hi>'s gueſt, that Love is a Magician. For how do ſouls kindle and conceive ſeeds of Love with a ſecret touch? How do Lovers like Inchanters burn and melt the diſſolving hearts of men by Images and repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? How do Beautiful eyes like thoſe of the <hi>Baſilisk,</hi> inchant the greedy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, inſinuating and interweaving their Raies with his till they knit Love knots, and manacle him look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backwards with chains of Embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? What elſe, were thoſe ſoft al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:106094:60"/>
by which <hi>Endymion</hi> charm'd the Moon out of her Orb? What elſe are thoſe enticing groans but Magick murmurs, <hi>Philtres</hi> of diſcourſe, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous numbers? What elſe but Charms of horrour, which with a blaſt of air ſtrike aſtoniſhment into the hearers? What elſe are Love-tokens but Spells which inſtill a ſweet Poiſon into thoſe who wear them? I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the powerful attractions of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon lov'd, deſerve my admiration more than the Magick figures of the Lovers obſequious poſtures, and inchanting blandiſhments, againſt which there isnot as in other inchantments the remedy of a <hi>Countercharm:</hi> neither indeed would we unbewitch our ſelves if we could, or reſiſt the pleaſing methods of our ruin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Truly all the force of Magick is in Love, which is ſaid to have the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous power of attracting things mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually together, and changing their Natures: becauſe the parts of the world like the members of a great Animal depending on the fame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and the Communion of the ſame Nature, are joyn'd together by one ſpirit informing the whole; and which
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:106094:60"/>
is the moſt certain ſign of union are collected into a Globe, ſo that one part returns upon the other in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual round. 'Tis by reaſon of this confederacy and ſecret Commerce of things; that by the mutual attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Souls, Love like a diſeaſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by Contagion invades chiefly the healthy, who yet by and by moſt willingly yield to the ſweet evil. And then the voluntary Captive more ſtraitly hugs his ſoft and ſilken fetters, then he is held by them, and does as little underſtand the Embraces which he enjoys as the chain it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Methinks I feel the reſtleſs Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Lovers more clearly than I deſcribe them, and ſeem to act my own argument <note place="margin">The argument of the work is ſumm'd up by the by. There is the ſame method of proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure in Philoſophy and Courtſhip. From kiſſes to Embraces, from a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and obſcure aſpect to intimate Viſions, from affection to nature, and thence to the cauſe of nature.</note> before I deliver it. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member heretofore when I was ſlightly deluded with dreams and Images, and ſcarce knew what I ſought after, I more truely endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the various tides of my but newly raging Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than I decyhper'd them. How did the firſt glance of my Miſtreſs not with a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:106094:61"/>
rude Image, but only the ſhadow of it, colour my blood, faſhion my thoughts, fix an impreſſion on my Soul, print my mind with her own Characters, laſtly ſeize the whole man and aſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late me to her ſelf! And yet there appear'd in my diſtemper'd breaſt no otherwiſe than in a troubled fountain, only an obſcure and uncertain form and ſhadow, ſuch as is feign'd to inhabit the regions of Death, languid and ſhy, flying all approaches and ſlipping through an Embrace. By and by lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up a little the Veil of <hi>Cupid</hi> and viewing with the greedineſs of a Wooer the Divine form of my juſt taſted felicity, <note place="margin">By ſo many ſteps and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees are inquired, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of Lovers, the effects and force of Love, the dowry and parentage whom it is convenient to Love, in what manner, what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for what end, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the degrees and kinds of loving.</note> my ignorance (as all al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt is) reſtleſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive, made me curious of examining every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, as what manners, what Dowry, what ſeat, what deſcent? For this uſes to be firſt and laſt in the Cares and joys of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, as to recollect the firſt ſportful eſſaies and rudiments of their Amours, ſo to make enquiry into the years and honours of their Parents, and to <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravel</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:106094:61"/>
their friendſhip back to its noble beginnings.</p>
            <p>Although it be a ſign of greatneſs &amp; <note place="margin">Thence enquiry is made into the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and natures of Love. Laſtly we aſcend up to the cauſes and Origin of Love.</note> antiquity, and has procured Religious reverence to many things to have their Originals beyond the date of Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, ſeal'd up to Oblivion as to Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, 'twill be no Crime I hope to relate &amp; adore the beginnings of love. Which is ſo happily obſcured by that conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of things, Antiquity, that like Heaven it has found a fabulous Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. I hear ſome telling me of <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludiums</hi> of Love, which Souls act in the <hi>Proſcenium</hi> of the other world, before they enter upon the <hi>Stage</hi> of this. I hear that ſouls deſcended from the Stars of their Nativity ſtill imitate their manners and conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. That as often as the wantonly diſpoſed Planets treat one another with Quintile aſpects, and burn with a nearer flame, then 'tis wooing time among men. That as aften as they mingle Embraces with their <hi>Conjugal</hi> Raies, then they kindle Marriage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torches here below. And laſtly that <note place="margin">The friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of men are not to be aſcribed to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, but to a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans nature.</note> they do not only ſhew us Mortals the way, and proſper us in it, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo make matches and betroth us here
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:106094:62"/>
on Earth. But to leave this fanciful argument, my Philoſophy aſſures me, 'tis not the heat of Heaven but that native one of the breaſt, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregates <hi>Homogeneous</hi> things, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flames men with an ardent Love of Society, either out of a zeal for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or out of a deſire to ſuccour infirmity, or a deſign of ſelf-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe, nature has im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted <note place="margin">Either to a zeal for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note> to every one, as a Tutelar Deity to each in particular, and as a common ſoul to all in general. Whence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever reſembles any part of a mans ſelf becomes ally'd to him on the ſcore of that ſimilitude. Hence Superiors are wedded to Inferiors in a mutual relation. Theſe ſtraitly embrace the other as their pattern and defence. The other protect theſe as their uten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſils and workmanſhip. But the eaſieſt aſſociation is between equals, becauſe free from the unconfiding awe which attends a Superior fortune, and the jarrings of untunable diſpoſitions. Whoever are Confederate by the Communion of nature enjoy ſo much the more pleaſure in their converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe they were moſt cloſely uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:106094:62"/>
even before any perſonal contract. <note place="margin">Or to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couring Infirmity.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But if any ſuppoſe that compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are repair'd to, as a defence of weakneſs, that to Love is a kind of begging, and that the Embraces of men like thoſe of the Vine and Ivie only ſeek out ſtronger props for their ſupport: Let him obſerve that for the Patronage of this infirmity, Love is feign'd to be a Boy, and that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and women, and whatſoever is of the infirmer ſort are moſt prone to Love. Let him obſerve that Vertues themſelves are ſought for by man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind only among the neceſſaries of life, and that they are either inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ambition, or reliefs of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digence. Let him know that all the terms of Alliance are indeed words which import ſuccour, and that by thoſe things which we honour with the moſt Sacred Titles, are unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood only the various Commodities of life. Theſe are the things (to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the truth) which we moſt loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call by the name of Brothers, Siſters and Parents. Neither is a friend eſteem'd any thing better than an <hi>Aſylum</hi> of refuge, and a proper poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:106094:63"/>
Laſtly, if we ſuppoſe men to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <note place="margin">Or to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of ſelf-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> by a fermenting appetite of ſelf Communication, and after the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God whoſe Image they bear, to make a <hi>Donative</hi> of themſelves; we ſhall think what's more Noble in its ſelf, and what's more worthy of that Sacred and ſociable Creature, and what comes neareſt to the Genius of Heaven, more freely to impart than receive an influence. For every man, as other Creatures are made for him, ſo he is born for more than himſelf only, and accordingly is ambitious of accommodating himſelf to others. As much as every one is aſhamed to confeſs his penury: So much does he delight to ſhew himſelf rich by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating his goods, rather than deſire the Alms of another. Hence we ſee ſome Souls <hi>Covetous</hi> of doing good, call in and adopt Aſſociates to ſhare with them in their felicity, and take it as a great kindneſs to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to have an occaſion given them of benefiting others. So that 'tis a greater pleaſure to have a friend in your proſperity, when you are in the Capacity to give, than in your adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, when you muſt always be on
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:106094:63"/>
the receiving hand. My own Planet has not been ſuch a niggard to me, that I ſhould want experiments of this liberality, or ſhould need a proof elſewhere. Nay even this very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of my gratitude con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning <note place="margin">A favour is more joyfully bellow'd than ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paid.</note> it ſelf, becauſe a favour is more joyfully beſtow'd than either receiv'd or repaid, does ſufficiently evidence that the genius of humane nature has preſcribed it ſelf this ſole way of doing of good, and out of a <hi>mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence</hi> of ſpirit has rejected the Laws of gratitude. Since the former pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from fullneſs of mind, the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is extorted by neceſſity. In the former there's the glory and ſtate of a Superior, in the latter the reverence and modeſty of an Inferior. He errs even to pity, dazled with the ſplendor of a more glorious fortune, who cannot <hi>endure</hi> a kindneſs; neither does he act ingratefuly nor proudly, but only mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificiently bent in ſpite of his <hi>unperfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi> fortune, and refuſing to yield in the Combat of generoſity, declares be would rather have been the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the kindneſs, which he had more munificently beſtow'd in wiſh before he receiv'd it. When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:106094:64"/>
you ſee ſome born to ſerve, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <note place="margin">Mankind is divided into two ſorts, ſome born to ſerve, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to protect and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. There is mutual benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them both, but they are more liberal who beſtow the man, than they who beſtow the goods. The Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin of friendſhip proceeds in the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as that of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</note> to cheriſh and defend; you turn over both the leaves not ſo much of fortune as of nature and benevolence. But you ſhould confeſs them Superior and more liberal who beſtow the man, than thoſe who with a <hi>cheap</hi> munificence permit an effuſion of their goods. So that either way the fire of Love does more willingly deſcend than aſcend. Nay this Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion always deſcends (ſince 'tis the part of the more excellent and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Love) and in a prone chanel is propagated through the degrees of alliance as man himſelf is.</p>
            <p>For there is the ſame method and procedure in the growth of friendſhip as in the conſtitution of Kingdoms. The heat firſt paſſing through the chanels of the blood creeps out of its own private encloſure into fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; then the vein burſting as it were with an eager fermentation, it expatiates farther to Allies and Fellow-Citizens. For we muſt return to them (leſt we ſhould ſeem to be more concern'd for the Dignity of Love than for truth, or be liable to blame for inſtituting other meaſures of lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:106094:64"/>
than what are popularly receiv'd, and for ſteering right againſt the ſtream) who propoſe us to our ſelves as patterns yea and cauſes of Love. For this is the merit of benevolence earneſtly to wiſh well to ones ſelf. This is the very deſign of a Lover to recover himſelf loſt in another, to cheriſh himſelf with the kindly heat, and by a certain vital energy to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert all into his own nouriſhment. So that 'tis no wonder that Vertue which enjoyns a neglect of our ſelves, ſuffers her ſelf a greater diſregard from the world. However let us not think it ſhame to be belov'd, as if this were to be mock'd and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected under the pretence of Officiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. You muſt know that every one Loves ill, but he that Loves himſelf; and that none in Loving themſelves deſign their own advantage, although by Loving they profit themſelves by accident. All Self-Love therefore <note place="margin">Self-love is a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thing by which we ardent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affect whatever we are or would be.</note> is a generous thing, by which we kindly affect whatever we are or would be, as what is or what ſhould be allyed to us. All of us are ſo touch'd with that ambition of ſome (who inſert the Armes and honours
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:106094:65"/>
of their Anceſtors among their own titles) that by a corruption of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauldry we adopt whatever is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent into the Table of our own kindred. So the emulous Cities contended about the praiſes of <hi>Homer</hi> in an unreconcileable War, as if for the inlargement of their Territories. Hence the ſplendor of vertue which is the chiefeſt ſecurity of Mortals, next of ſelf-love, kindles thoſe of taking diſpoſitions at the firſt flaſh, and that which adores the Deity is adored it ſelf. Whoſe power is ſuch that there is none of ſo deſperate impiety who is not in his wiſh and approbation, I had almoſt ſaid mind too, good; Who would not he had exerciſed that Vertue which as yet he does not, and who does not heartily Embrace that Vertue in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, which, he does ill away with in himſelf.</p>
            <p>Whither does this firſt impulſe not <note place="margin">From this double impulſe of nature and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the firſt impulſe of reaſon carries us to what we would be. Hence the firſt cauſes of Love are Vertue and its ſhadows with whatſoever carries the ſemblance of it.</note> of nature only but reaſon carry us? cheated with a voluntary impoſture
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:106094:65"/>
we fall proſtrate before not only Vertue, but any thing which bears the leaſt ſhadow or appearance of it. Sometimes that difficulty (which guards the path of Vertue with a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred horrour, and keeps off the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane rabble) puſhes us forward, and intices with its indearing injuries. The honey of Lips gains a more exquiſite relliſh from the interpoſals of ſtings. To watch at the Window of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, to ſuffer a repulſe from a mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Rival or to be diſreſpectfully uſed, are all but ſpurs to future pleaſure, like as ſqueezing the hand, and wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lip with the eager rudeneſs of a biting kiſs. Sometimes rarity (which through the ſloth of the age ſeems almoſt peculiar to vertue) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends Monſters to our fancy and all outlandiſh deformity.</p>
            <p>'Tis well known alſo how preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent are thoſe allurements of Lovers which are rank'd among the chiefeſt ſhadows of Vertues, praiſes, which are dearer to women than their looking-glaſs or box of perfumes, with which as with incenſe men as well as Gods are appeas'd. How eaſy is it by this art to pleaſe both our ſelves
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:106094:66"/>
and others! How eaſie is it by theſe pretious blandiſhments to pleaſe the moſt Chaſt Matron! For all even the moſt modeſt, love to be commended, and thoſe who refuſe to be lov'd are yet ambitious of appearing lovely. Both are arguments of a mind ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly diſpoſed, though to praiſe be a more certain one than to be prais'd. For to be prais'd is frequently the <hi>lot,</hi> always the <hi>ambition</hi> of the moſt undeſerving, as deformed perſons covet paint. But none can praiſe and himſelf not be laudable. He does the ſame or would do who approves, and is illuſtrated from the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of another: As he that erects a Statue to the memory of an Heroe, erects alſo at the ſame time to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Monument of Vertue. For this ſeems an high flight of merit not to exerciſe vertues, but what's more, to reverence and adore them. Theſe are thoſe darts of <hi>Cupid</hi> which are pointed with his feathers, which while they tickle, wound the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and like Arrows deliver'd ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and at a diſtance, reach thoſe who are moſt remov'd from us. But to make flattering preambles and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:106094:66"/>
               <hi>bribe</hi> Benevolence (the uſual art of Rhetoricians and Lovers) ſeems all one to me as to dawb the lips with paint preparatively to an Embrace, which always inſtils a ſweet Poyſon, and inſenſibly corrodes the kiſſes.</p>
            <p>So much are we men the <hi>Creatures</hi> of glory and Vertue, that I fear <note place="margin">Among vertues theſe more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ones cauſe Love.</note> 'twould not be much for our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to confeſs, that among Vertues we Embrace them moſt which are profitable. Whether they be thoſe which exerciſe and invite humanity, as modeſty and equity; or thoſe which preſide over and protect it as forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and munificence. Which, when we our ſelves are no way advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taged by them, we gratulate in the behalf of others. But as Emulation, ſo munificence indears our affections to other vertues. Although its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence be ſo much the greater by how much the receiver is leſs deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. Becauſe then the kindneſs is wholely to be aſcribed not to the judgment, but favour of the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, and becauſe for our ſakes he would run the hazard of being <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfully</hi> beneficial. This liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:106094:67"/>
is no ſooner above the Horizon, but that other which is inbred in the heart of mankind ſhines parallel to it. And although perhaps at firſt by an erroneous eſtimation it valued the giver for the ſake of his gifts, yet afterwards it values the gifts for the Authour, whoſe parental indulgence extended it ſelf beyond the partition-wall of his own family, and adopted a ſtranger with the ſame domeſtick affection as an Allie into his <hi>Hoſpitable</hi> boſom. Here over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loaded gratitude faints, and finding it ſelf uncapable of returning any thing beſides the man, repays its Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron as a Deity with the bare Votary. And truly in my opinion he betraies no ſuch generous ardour of mind who returns benefits as Debts, and <hi>pays</hi> gifts, that he may quit ſcores, and that accounts may be kept even on both ſides, as if they were dealing on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a more liberal way of uſury. 'Tis not affection but pride, which makes a man ſo impatient of lying under an obligation. This is not to receive but <hi>retort</hi> kindneſſes: This is with more diſdain than gratitude
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:106094:67"/>
to boaſt riches in a contention of munificence. But ſince true benefits aim at nothing but a kind reception, he only knows how to be a <hi>liberal</hi> receiver who candidly interprets, and retaliates nothing, but a grateful mind. Neither does he think this any valuable return of his own libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, but only the pledge of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. But leſt any one ſhould think I inſinuate this as an Apology for my incapacity or ingratitude, let him know that I have perſwaded my ſelf that friends give with that Candor as if they paid only that they might owe, and return gifts with ſuch free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as thoſe that give of their own accord. Theſe are benefits, theſe are thoſe Arrows of <hi>Cupid</hi> which with a <note place="margin">Benefits are the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of <hi>Cupid</hi> arm'd with gold.</note> Golden point give a <hi>Splendid</hi> but <hi>faithful</hi> wound. More powerful truly is the Courtſhip of <hi>Jupiter</hi> under gold than under feathers, or the Rays of his Divinity. For gifts are the univerſal Character, whereas 'tis the Talent only of ſome few to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Idiom of Majeſty, and the ſoothing flouriſh of a Rhetorical Pen.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:106094:68"/>
Shall I now ſay that from this gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <note place="margin">From li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality ariſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſoftens he breaſt and then ſigns it with an Image.</note> humanity of mind proceeds a good natur'd Commiſeration, which ſoftens the breaſt like Wax, and then ſeals it with any Image? Or that from this ampleneſs of mind flows that <hi>proud</hi> benignity, which while it ſeeks occaſion to exerciſe munificence, Loves the miſerable even to Paſſion, and ſcorns the happy? Or ſhall I think that from hence ariſes a generous Statelineſs which is more ambitious of bow'd knees and heads than Embraces, and Loves only on this <hi>Magnificent</hi> condition, that it be not Lov'd again? Or rather ſhall I term this a ſoft modeſty, like to theirs who can endure to eye an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other till he look back upon them?</p>
            <p>And now we confeſs with thee <note place="margin">Beauty is rank'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Vertues, which holds forth an animated ſyſtem of Ethicks and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes in the body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>Il the Vertues, prudence, fortitude, juſtice and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> 
               <hi>Plato,</hi> the divineſt of all Prophets, a wonderful ſcene of Love diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play'd throughout the whole body, where Vertue expoſes herſelf to view, where the Candor of the mind tempers the blood with a milky whiteneſs, and modeſty dies the Cheek with a ſweet Vermilion;
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:106094:68"/>
where the liberal forehead <hi>hoſpitably</hi> entertains the beholders; and the glances of the eye are gather'd up like ſcatter'd gems; where you may perceive the <hi>diſcipline</hi> of a compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed countenance, gravely checking and allaying thoſe ſparks which it kindled in you by its Beauty. Where you may obſerve the dictates of a quick appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending aſpect, and imbibe <hi>tacit</hi> leſſons of prudence; where you may ſee regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly diſpoſed by a certain ballance of juſtice the even meaſures as of manners ſo of the limbs, and peruſe a <hi>living</hi> ſyſtem of Ethicks with your <note place="margin">Hence 'tis call'd a Corporeal Vertue.</note> eyes; where, when you ſhall behold the lucid members joynted to one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other like gems both for Ornament and ſervice, wondring a while at the compacted ſtrength of <hi>ſolid</hi> Beauty, you will cry out, Hither <hi>Vulcan</hi> with thy nets! behold, we have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken again <hi>Mars</hi> accompanying <hi>Venus</hi>! This is a Beauty worth the Empire of more than one world. Thanks be to <hi>Jupiter</hi> and his Eagle, that the earth is not envy'd the poſſeſſion of ſo great Beauty. Hence the Divine <hi>Plato</hi> may with rapture and ecſtaſie
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:106094:69"/>
deduce Theorems of Philoſophy, and contemplate a fairer Idea with his <hi>eyes</hi> than ever he did with his <hi>mind. Socrates</hi> may ſend his delicate youth to trim themſelves at the ſuperlative luſtre of this face as at a looking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſs. And here <hi>Eudoxus</hi> fall'n from his admiration of the Sun, may affirm mankind was made on purpoſe to view this light, and to feaſt on <hi>bright</hi> pleaſures, though to the loſs of their eyes. There are more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Charms in the aſpect of this form, than in <hi>Orpheus</hi> his lyre to tame wild beaſts and Philoſophers. This Splendor more delightſome than day-light, is fitter than the Sun to try and educate the off-ſpring not of Eagles only but of mankind too. I would almoſt ſwear that our ſouls deſcended from the Skie as falling Stars, they are ſo inamour'd with all Brightneſs. Theſe are the Arrows of <hi>Cupid</hi> pointed with the light of eyes, and ſparkling out flames, which <hi>ſhine, burn</hi> and <hi>wound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus whatſoever is excellent, <note place="margin">All Love is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in likeneſs.</note> whatſoever we would be like to, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts us to it ſelf with the ſame ardour,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:106094:69"/>
as we do thoſe things which we ſeem <note place="margin">Where fore we all Love ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whom we would be like to, or whom we are. From the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ariſe thoſe ſpurs of a taſted Love; from the latter, firſt ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude it ſelf;</note> already to reſemble. We mutually crave and give Pardon to this mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ours which makes us do the ſame when men as when children, <hi>viz.</hi> to reach out to kiſs our Pictures in Looking-glaſſes. 'Tis the Fate of all mankind as well as of <hi>Narciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> to be Paſſionately in Love with their own repreſentations. And 'tis but juſt that we more zealouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect our other ſelf than our Parents or Children, who are but pieces of our ſelves, or than an Artificer does his own work which is only the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and Image of his art. 'Tis an excuſable greedineſs which prompts us to feed upon our like, ſince 'tis the nature of our ſouls as well as bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to require conſimilar aliment. Wherefore I don't wonder at the <note place="margin">Then Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom;</note> bewitching power of Cuſtom, which recommends to our affections not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faces but places themſelves and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>animate trifles, as if they were our Companions. Whence the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay which inſenſibly preys upon Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, adds alſo grace to deformity.</p>
            <p>For the eye and mind tinctured
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:106094:70"/>
with a familiar ſpecies, ſee no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er but through painted glaſs, which takes off from the horror of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. So alſo familiarity without <note place="margin">Then fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity.</note> which we are remote even when pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, adds this force to cuſtom, that it may form <hi>Twin manners,</hi> by a reciprocal generation beget a <hi>Conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity</hi> of diſpoſitions and adapt mind to mind, till anothers conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is more ſweet and free to us than our own. What? 'Tis torment not ſociety to be under a conſtant fear of diſpleaſing, to compoſe all things to the worſt of Looking glaſſes that of a face (ſince we can't to the others mind) to order our Commerce with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verential concern, to weigh our words like gold before we deliver them, to preſent our ſelves at a ſet meeting with premeditate geſture, and then there to behave our ſelves as in a Theatre.</p>
            <p>But Why do I mention thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimilar <note place="margin">Alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of ſimilitude, Love.</note> ſpecies which either nature, art or Cuſtom ſlightly imprints on our minds? When 'tis Love which gives all theſe a lively ſtamp, by whoſe power alone (the ſoul having long ſince took her leave) they are actua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:106094:70"/>
and enliven'd. Happy is it for Lovers, that perſons may Love even againſt their wills. Since your Lover is not only like, but the ſame with your ſelf, he has ſtoln away you from your ſelf unawares; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your leave. There is no need that he demand returns of kindneſs and <hi>Debts</hi> of Love. If this be nothing available with you that he is your Image, your ſlave, your proper goods; that for your ſake he parted with his ſoul and liberty; If you nothing dread the Crime of cruelty and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, yet by the neceſſity of nature Love kindles Love, flame kindles flame. Yet nature would not grant Love the power to counterfeit, or if counterfeit to burn any otherwiſe than painted fire. For though the face, aſpect and geſture feign never ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly, yet the ſimulation will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray it ſelf as all painted things do, either by a too emulous or a too re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs endeavour of imitation. If you don't yet acknowledge that Love is the price of a man; yet at leaſt that you may admit it to be ſo under the ſordid Name of benefit, know,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:106094:71"/>
that it compriſes in it ſelf all the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits which it beſtows, and which it cannot beſtow, and in wiſh more than all. Without which I ſhall aſcribe the benefits themſelves to fortune and fate, not to the man, and ſhall think them rather <hi>found</hi> than <hi>receiv'd.</hi> By which alone the poor man acts libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, as often as he gives nothing, but wiſhes munificently. Than which nothing greater is either expected from or render'd to Mortals by the Gods. Here's a Philtre of more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence than any herb. <hi>If you will be lov'd, Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as it betrays meanneſs of ſoul to require and render reaſons why we Love, ſo that Love is more inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous which like ſome flowers ſprings up without any ſeed, and has this of Eternity, to exiſt without a cauſe, and like Heaven to be mov'd by an <hi>inviſible</hi> Intelligence. We find now that that ſimilitude whether manifeſt <note place="margin">Similitude whether manifeſt or occult which is call'd ſympathy, is all Love</note> or occult which goes under the name of <hi>Sympathy,</hi> is all nothing elſe but <hi>Love.</hi> Whence without any nearneſs or familiarity, the near and familiar ſoul cloſes faſt, and ſquares exactly
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:106094:71"/>
to another. Juſt as Mathematicians ſay one plain body adheres to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſeparably, united only by the <hi>Cement</hi> of conformity. Nature ſeems to bring forth <hi>Twin-minds,</hi> and to aſſign mates to ſouls as ſhadows and Genius's to bodies, or as Nymphs Co-eval to their Trees. Hence men in ſpight of their Aſcendent undergo the ſame Stars and Fates, and in all reſpects are Twins. O the unpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd generoſity of theſe well match'd Lovers, a more Noble ſpectacle than a couple of Gladiators! Where the <hi>Duel</hi> of liberality is all fought in Offices of mutual kindneſs. In this one thing there is diſcord in their affections, that both being over ſolicitous for each other are diſquieted with hatred and fears. Both as if tinctur'd with each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Choler ſee and judge the ſame. Both as if touch'd with the ſame Load-ſtone, tend to the ſame point in all their deſigns and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours. The one repreſents the others face more faithfully than a Looking-glaſs. The one imitates the others manners more punctually than
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:106094:72"/>
a Paraſite. So that even he himſelf is not ſo much like himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>While I was Scribling at this rate,</hi> Cupid <hi>ſnatch'd my pen out of my hand, and flew away with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:106094:72"/>
            <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>SInce the Commiſſion of this Book to the Preſs, there came to my hand a Tranſlation (if it deſerve that name) of <hi>Effigies Amoris,</hi> upon the peruſal of which, I was ſo far from being induced to recal mine, that I found I had now a greater reaſon than ever to make it publick, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the vindication of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and much abuſed Author. The <hi>Sacrilegious</hi> Tranſlator is as much a ſtranger to me as he is to the Idi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>om of the Latine Tongue; and therefore I ſhall deal more civilly with him, than to give any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar inſtances of his failures, and ſhall only ſay in general, That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Omiſſions and miſtakes the Author is utterly loſt. I had not ſaid thus much, had I not thought my ſelf obliged to conſult the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
<pb facs="tcp:106094:73"/>
Credit more than the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, leſt any ſhould judge the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Beauty by the injurious repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of a falſe <hi>Glaſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:106094:73"/>
            <head>ERRATA</head>
            <p>PAG. 15. l. 22. for <hi>poliſh,</hi> r. <hi>polliſh.</hi> p. 19. for <hi>never,</hi> r. <hi>even.</hi> p. 67. l. 8. for <hi>one ſelf,</hi> r. <hi>ones ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What other literal faults there are, or falſe pointings, the Reader is deſired to give him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the trouble of correcting.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:106094:74"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106094:74"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Tho. Sawbridge,</hi> at the <hi>Three Flower de Luces</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>BP. <hi>Sanderſons</hi> Sermons, Folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bakers</hi> Chronicle, Folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Guillim's</hi> Heraldry, Folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cooks</hi> Reports (Eng.) Folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wilſon's</hi> Chriſtian Dictionary, Folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wanly,</hi> Wonders of the Little World.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cauſſin's</hi> Holy Court, Folio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bacon's</hi> Advancement of Learning, Folio.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
